<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Kitchin-physician, or, A guide for good-housewives in maintaining their families in health wherein are described the natures, causes, and symptoms of all diseases, inward and outward, incident to the bodies of men, women, and children : prescribing natural, useful and proper published for the common good ... by T.K., Doctor in Physick.</title>
            <author>T. K., Doctor in physick.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 165 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 75 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47169</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K20</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18406</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12349688</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12349688</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59943</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47169)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59943)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 213:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Kitchin-physician, or, A guide for good-housewives in maintaining their families in health wherein are described the natures, causes, and symptoms of all diseases, inward and outward, incident to the bodies of men, women, and children : prescribing natural, useful and proper published for the common good ... by T.K., Doctor in Physick.</title>
                  <author>T. K., Doctor in physick.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 134 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Lee ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: film lacks sculptures.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine, Popular --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59943:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> THE Kitchin-Phyſician: OR, A GUIDE FOR GOOD-HOUSEWIVES IN Maintaining their Families in health.</p>
            <p>Wherein are deſcribed The Natures, Cauſes, and Symptoms of all Diſeaſes inward and outward, incident to the Bodies of Men, Women, and Children.</p>
            <p>Preſcribing natural, uſeful, and proper Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines both in Phyſick and Chirurgery, as well for the prevention as ſpeedy Cure of the ſaid Diſtempers.</p>
            <p>Adorned with Sculptures, ſhewing the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per place of every Diſtemper in the Body.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed for the common good of City &amp; Country, By <hi>T. K.</hi> Doctor in Phyſick.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Lee,</hi> Stationer, over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Poſt-Office in <hi>Lumbard-ſtreet.</hi> 1680.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:59943:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:59943:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>I Have here ſet before your view, a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the rich Garden of Nature, adorned with nothing but its own ſimple qualities; which at firſt was not obliged to any of the Learned to Tranſlate it into Galenical Compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or any Artificial Experiments, but was made uſe on by our fore-Fathers, for their relief in Sickneſs and Malady, long before Phyſick was brought into a Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the Profeſſors of it courted by the Ignorant, when they received (in ordinary and common Diſtempers) little more than a bare Complement from them, ſave one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly referring them to their Mother Nature, the true and original Healer of ſuch Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes. And although this ſmall Attempt may receive Oppoſition from ſome mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirited Phyſitians, whoſe Intereſt may be invaded by the Publication of it, and who are Impoſtors of Phyſick, with pretended Univerſal Medicines: Yet my deſign is, (though bred up a Phyſitian) to leave this as a Legacy to my Country, before my gray hairs go down to the Grave, purely to make them their own Phyſitians in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes not dubious, nor requiring the utmoſt improvement of Nature, into a well-dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted
<pb facs="tcp:59943:3"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:59943:4"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:59943:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:59943:5"/> and conſulted concluſion of Art. And by the way, I would not have the Reader think, that I have the leaſt ill Opinion of the Elaborate Inventions, and ingenious Experiments of the Learned, in bringing Phyſick to the utmoſt perfection; for I have a great adoration for all ſuch wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Improvers of Nature: but I am not of Opinion, that their aſſiſtance is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in common and ordinary diſtempers, which many times the diligent Nurſe, or Houſewife, by her plain and common Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience in Herbs and Plants, cures, when they by their ſublime and too high ſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed applications, leave the Patient in a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate condition. And therefore I hope theſe my poor endeavours will be kindly entertained by ſuch of my Country-men as will not entertain prejudice thereto be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-hand; and do not fear that any Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Phyſitian will think ill of this Publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, (eſpecially if what it contains be true and certain, as I hope it is) his Buſineſs and Imployment being of a far higher nature, <hi>De ordine Naturae,</hi> and ſeeming rather by his great attempt, as it were, to diſpute with our great Mother her ſelf, in matters where ſhe is ſometimes at a <hi>Ne plus ultra.</hi> This I thought good to premiſe to the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Reader, and heartily wiſh that it may anſwer my honeſt deſign therein. Farewel.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. K.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:59943:5"/>
            <head>A TABLE of the ſeveral Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers incident to the Bodies of Men and Women, anſwering the before-going Cut; to which the ſeveral Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphs in the enſuing Book do likewiſe particularly refer, in Arithmetical order.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1. HOw to clear the Face.</item>
               <item>2. How to take away Sunburning from the face.</item>
               <item>3. Of Freckles, Spots, or</item>
               <item>4. Wrinkles in the Face.</item>
               <item>5. How to ſoften the roughneſs of the Skin, and take away the Chops of the Lips and Hands.</item>
               <item>6. How to make your hands that are yellow and wrinkled, ſmooth.</item>
               <item>7. How to take away Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>8. To leſſen the appearance of a vein between the Eyes.</item>
               <item>9. How to cure a Red Face.</item>
               <item>10. Againſt Burning and Bliſtering.</item>
               <item>11. How to cure the Pox, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcerations proceeding from thence.</item>
               <item>12. To make Pock-holes ſmooth.</item>
               <item>13. To take away Scabs and Scurf which eat into the skin.</item>
               <item>14. Againſt White Scabs or Sores.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:59943:6"/>
               <item> 15. How to remedy the ſhedding or falling of the Hair.</item>
               <item>16. How to make white or gray hairs black.</item>
               <item>17. How to kill Nits and 18. Lice.</item>
               <item>19. How to cure the ſtinging of Venemous Beaſts.</item>
               <item>20. A perfect cure for the Head-ach, occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by Heat, Cold, or Drunkenneſs.</item>
               <item>21. A Cure for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers of the Skull.</item>
               <item>22. How to cure Madneſs.</item>
               <item>23. To cure the Lethargy.</item>
               <item>24. To proc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Sleep.</item>
               <item>25. To cure the giddineſs of the Head.</item>
               <item>26. How to cure the Falling Sickneſs, and to be preſerved from it.</item>
               <item>27. How to cure the dead Palſey.</item>
               <item>28. How to cure the Apoplexy.</item>
               <item>29. How to cure the ſhaking Palſey.</item>
               <item>30. How to ſtrengthen the Eyes.</item>
               <item>31. To cure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that are ſubject to water.</item>
               <item>32. To cure weeping Eyes, and Humours that fall down into them.</item>
               <item>33. To take away the Redneſs of the Eyes.</item>
               <item>34. To cure the Inflammation of the Eyes.</item>
               <item>35. To take red ſpots out of the Eyes.</item>
               <item>36. To cleanſe the Eyes from all filthy mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</item>
               <item>37. To take ſpots and webs out of the Eye.</item>
               <item>38. To take away the pain of the Eyes.</item>
               <item>39. To cure the pain of the Ears, proceeding from hot cauſes.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:59943:6"/>
               <item> 40. A Remedy for Thickneſs of Hearing.</item>
               <item>41. Againſt Deafneſs.</item>
               <item>42. Againſt Worms in the Ears.</item>
               <item>43. Againſt Noiſe in the Ears.</item>
               <item>44. How to cure little Boils or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the Ears.</item>
               <item>45. Againſt the Swelling or Kings-evil in the Neck.</item>
               <item>46. Againſt the ſtopping of the Noſe.</item>
               <item>47. How Humours that run out of the Noſe may be ſtopped.</item>
               <item>48. A remedy againſt Sneezing.</item>
               <item>49. A Medicine to recover the Smelling, when 'tis loſt or corrupted.</item>
               <item>50. To ſtaunch the exceſſive Bleeding of the Noſe.</item>
               <item>51. To cure the Boils and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers of the Noſe.</item>
               <item>52. A Remedy againſt the ſtinking of the Noſe.</item>
               <item>53. A Remedy againſt the ſtinking of the Mouth.</item>
               <item>54. How to cure an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcerous Mouth.</item>
               <item>55. To cure exceſſive ſlabbering.</item>
               <item>56. How to cleanſe the Teeth, and keep them ſound.</item>
               <item>57. To faſten looſe Teeth.</item>
               <item>58. Of Hollow Teeth.</item>
               <item>59. A Remedy againſt the Tooth-ach.</item>
               <item>60. Of ſharp Teeth.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:59943:7"/>
               <item> 61. A cure for a ſtinking Breath.</item>
               <item>62. A cure for the Squinancy.</item>
               <item>63. Againſt Hoarſneſs.</item>
               <item>64. Againſt Purſineſs, or ſhortneſs of breath.</item>
               <item>65. A Remedy for a Cough.</item>
               <item>67. A cure for the Pluriſie.</item>
               <item>68. A cure for a Conſumption.</item>
               <item>69. A cure for the Paſſion of the Heart.</item>
               <item>70. A Remedy againſt Faintneſs.</item>
               <item>71. A cure for a conſtant Ague.</item>
               <item>72. For a quotidian Ague.</item>
               <item>73. For a Tertian Feaver.</item>
               <item>74. For a quartan Ague.</item>
               <item>75. For Shaking, and in an Ague.</item>
               <item>76. Thirſt, in an Ague.</item>
               <item>77. A cure for the Plague, and ſwelling So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> thereof.</item>
               <item>78. A Remedy for hanging Breaſts.</item>
               <item>79. A cure for an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcerated Breaſt.</item>
               <item>80. How to breed and increaſe Milk.</item>
               <item>81. To dry up Milk.</item>
               <item>82. A Remedy to prevent any evil which may come by the Biting of Adders, or other venemous Creatures.</item>
               <item>83. A Remedy againſt the Hiccough.</item>
               <item>84. A cure for Belching.</item>
               <item>85. To ſtrengthen the ſtomach.</item>
               <item>86. A cure for a Nauſeating ſtomach.</item>
               <item>87. An help againſt Vomiting in an Ague.</item>
               <item>88. A cure for an aking ſtomach.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:59943:7"/>
               <item> 89. A cure for the Worms.</item>
               <item>90. A cure for the griping of the Guts.</item>
               <item>91. A Remedy againſt all Obſtructions.</item>
               <item>92. A cure for the Flux.</item>
               <item>93. A Remedy for the bleeding of the Paps.</item>
               <item>94. A cure for the pain of the Paps.</item>
               <item>95. A cure for an hot Liver.</item>
               <item>96. How to cure the Obſtructions of the Liver.</item>
               <item>97. A Remedy for the Jaundice.</item>
               <item>98. A cure for the Black Jaundice.</item>
               <item>99. A cure for the Dropſie.</item>
               <item>100. A cure for the Obſtruction of the Spleen.</item>
               <item>101. A Remedy for the pain of the Spleen.</item>
               <item>102. A cure for the Collick, occaſioned by Gravel.</item>
               <item>103. A Remedy for the Stone in the Reins.</item>
               <item>104. For the Stone in the Bladder.</item>
               <item>105. A Remedy for hot Piſſing.</item>
               <item>106. A cure for thoſe who cannot hold their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine.</item>
               <item>107. A Remedy againſt drop-piſſing.</item>
               <item>108. A Remedy againſt painful Piſſing.</item>
               <item>109. A cure for the Inflammation of the Privy-Members.</item>
               <item>110. A cure for an Inflamed Womb or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix.</item>
               <item>111. For the Riſing of the Mother.</item>
               <item>112. For the ſinking downward of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</item>
               <item>113. A Remedy for the White Flux.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:59943:8"/>
               <item> 114. For an exceſſive Menſtrual Flux.</item>
               <item>115. For the ſtopping of the Monthly Flux.</item>
               <item>116. How to take away Barrenneſs.</item>
               <item>117. A Remedy againſt Miſcarrying.</item>
               <item>118. To procure Eaſe in hard Labour.</item>
               <item>119. To eaſe pangs or Throws after Child-bearing.</item>
               <item>120. A Remedy againſt the perturbation of the Mother.</item>
               <item>121. For a Rupture.</item>
               <item>122. A cure for the Gout.</item>
               <item>123. For a Red ſwelling.</item>
               <item>124. For a windy Swelling.</item>
               <item>125. A Remedy againſt Apoſtems, Tumours, or hard ſwellings.</item>
               <item>126. Againſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcerous Swellings.</item>
               <item>127. A cure for the Itch.</item>
               <item>128. For Boils and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers.</item>
               <item>129. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers of the Nails. 130. Bad <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers.</item>
               <item>131. Cancker. 132. Knobs.</item>
               <item>133. For a Fall. 134. Bruiſes.</item>
               <item>135. Freſh Wounds. 136. All kind of Wounds.</item>
               <item>137. Shot-Wounds. 138. Stamped Sinews.</item>
               <item>139. Stung Sinews.</item>
               <item>140. Sinews cut through.</item>
               <item>141. Inward Wounds.</item>
               <item>142. Biting of a Mad Dog.</item>
               <item>143. Biting of a Serpent.</item>
               <item>144. Kibes on the Heels.</item>
               <item>145. Stinking Feet.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59943:8"/>
            <head>THE Kitchin-Phyſician: OR, A guide for good Houſe-wifes, In maintaining The Health of their Families.</head>
            <p>AS it is neceſſary for the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Health, to keep our Houſes neat and cleanly; ſo we ſhould be careful to keep our Bodies free from putrifying Diſeaſes. And becauſe the Faces of Men (eſpecially of Women) are (more than any other part of the Body) expoſed to view; I will write of Medicines which adorn that part, by adding Comelineſs and Beauty thereunto. Beauty is a bleſſing which every one ought to preſerve, and not to neglect.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>1. <hi>Of Medicines and other Remedies which are appropriated to the Skin, Hair, and Teeth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>For the Cleanſing of the Bodies of Men
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59943:9"/> and Women, Bathings are very uſeful, and may be thus made.</p>
               <p>Take of Sage-leaves, Flowers of Laven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and Roſes, of each one handful, with a little Salt; let all theſe boil in Fountain or River-water to a Bath.</p>
               <p>Or, take Roſe-water, Wine-Vineger, and Salt, of each a little; let them boil to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in common water, (as much as in your diſcretion you ſhall think ſufficient) until there remain two or three Pails: af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward put a Wheaten-Roll or Loaf therein; then rub the whole Body with the ſame: and after you have ſo done, go into a luke-warm Bath, and remain there as long as you can.</p>
               <p>Or, take water of Orange-flowers, Red and White Roſes, of each one ounce, ſix Lemon-Pills, Cloves a quarter of an ounce, Flower de Luce of Florence the eighth part of an ounce; let theſe Ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients ſoak five or ſix hours in the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid waters; then ſtrain them through a clean cloth, and add thereunto five Pints of ſweet Almond-Milk; theſe being ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led together, are for the waſhing of your Body, (having firſt bathed in a Bath of luke-warm water.)</p>
               <p>The vertues of theſe Baths are theſe: They comfort the Sinews, they take away
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:59943:9"/> all foulneſs of the skin, they exhilerate and refreſh the Spirits. Theſe and the like are uſeful for Men and Women: but the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Ingredients are moſt proper for Women, foraſmuch as their chiefeſt vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is to make the Face fair, to procure and preſerve Beauty; of theſe Imbelliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments men have no need. And they may be performed without Painting-ſtuff, which impaireth Beauty. Theſe waters are made of ſuch things, that (for the moſt part) are gotten in Gardens. Painting is pernicious; for it is the cauſe of wrinkles; of a ſtinking breath, of black and looſe teeth, of redneſs of Eyes, weakneſs of ſight, deafneſs, and other infirmities, which happen to thoſe who paint their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and take more care to appear (by that impudent means) beautiful, than to preſerve the Health of their whole bodies. Theſe are the evil effects of the uſe of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limated White-lead, and ſuch like things, which are as dangerous as: the Plague. And now I will ſhew<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>How to make the face Beautiful, White, Smooth, and Red.</head>
                  <p>By the uſe of theſe following Beauty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waters, Ladies may preſerve their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexions,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59943:10"/> with ſafety to their Health.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An excellent Water.</head>
                  <p>Take of white and ſmooth ſhaled Beans, one pound, let them ſoak nine or ten days in Whitewine; then (having poun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them ſufficiently in a Stone-Morter) put them again into the ſaid Wine, adding thereto, of Goats Milk two quarts, of Flour of Rice half a pound, the whites of twelve Eggs: all this you muſt ſet over a little fire in a Colb, or Stilling-glaſs. With this ſtilled water the Face is to be waſhed at night when you go to Bed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another Water.</head>
                  <p>Take a wheaten Loaf of two pounds, the whites of eight or ten Eggs, ſtrong Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neger according to diſcretion; mix theſe all together, and being put into water, ſtill them through a glaſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another Water.</head>
                  <p>Take twenty four Eggs, and having waſhed them clean, break them, and beat them, ſhells, yolks, and white, well toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, adding thereto, white-Wine two pints, Goats Milk one pint, Flour of Beans one handful: put theſe into hot water, then ſtill them through a Colb or Stilling-glaſs. Let this water thus ſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, ſtand fifteen days in the Sun, then it will be fit for your purpoſe. When you
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59943:10"/> uſe it, warm a little of it, and diſſolve therein Burra, Sugar-Candy powdered, of each a like quantity: with this you muſt waſh your Face in the Morning and at Night.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another Water.</head>
                  <p>Take the Crum of White-bread, Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Lillies, Roſes, of each one pound; Elder-berries, Flour of Beans, of each half a pound; ſtrong Wine-Vinegar, Goats Milk two pints, the whites of four Eggs; diſtil them together through a Glaſs, as above, in hot water.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another Water.</head>
                  <p>Take five Lemmons and cut them in pieces, three Apples, Sugar, Allum, of each an ounce; diſtil them through a Glaſs, as before.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another Water.</head>
                  <p>Take the Roots of Pignuts being well waſhed, cut them into ſmall ſlices, and put them into a glaſed pot, (contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing five Engliſh pints) half full, twelve Egg-ſhells well waſh'd and bruiſed, one pint and ſomewhat more of White-Wine, Rain and River-water, until the pot be full; let all theſe boil together, until a third part be boil'd away, adding thereto the crum of a ſmall white Loaf, Spaniſh Green of the bigneſs of a Bean. Bind
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59943:11"/> all theſe in a little bag; bray or bruiſe the ſaid Decoction on a Tile, while it is luke-warm, at laſt put into it one ounce of Sugar. Wet a fine cloath therein, and waſh your face at Night and in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, without wiping it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another Water.</head>
                  <p>Bore the Stem (or Trunk) of a Birch-Tree with an Iron Bore, and much water will run out of it, which is uſeful on this occaſion, and alſo to take away Sun-burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. There are many other Waters that clear the Face, which I paſs by for brevity ſake; I ſhall onely add hereto</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Dove or Pigeon-water, which is made thus.</head>
                  <p>Take two white Pigeons, pluck them, draw out their guts, throw them into a Stilling-glaſs, upon a rank of leaves of Aſh-herb, (called Fraxinella, or wild Dita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,) Lambs Tongue two handfuls: lay them upon the floor, then add thereto freſh Butter four ounces, Oyl of ſweet Almonds three ounces, Buras, Champher, Burnt Allum, and Sugar Candy powdered, the crum of a white Loaf, the whites of twenty five Eggs, two handfuls of the kernels of Grapes, Goats Milk four pints.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59943:11"/> Let theſe ſoak ten or twelve hours in the ſtilling-glaſs, well ſtop'd. Let it diſtil ſlowly in a water-Bath (or <hi>balneo Mariae)</hi> put the divided Water into Flasks, in a cool Cellar, then ſtrain it through a clean and fine Cloth. Waſh your face with this water in the morning and at night with a little cloth.</p>
                  <p>Beſides theſe waters, there are alſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Oyntments of great uſe: and Oyls and Pomades.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Oyntment.</head>
                  <p>Boyl two Eggs hard, cut them in the midſt, take out the yolk, fill the hollow with the powder of burnt Wine-ſtone; join the half parts together, and tye them with a thred; put them into a diſh, and ſet them in a moiſt Cellar. The Wine-ſtone will melt, whereby the moiſtneſs running through the white of the Eggs, will alter (together with that which comes thereby) to an Oyl, ſuch as you deſire.</p>
                  <p>Oyl of the Acorns of an Oak, being preſſed out, as that of Almonds, and mingled with that of the Egg-ſhels, is uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to make the face beautiful. Alſo</p>
                  <p>Oyl of Myrrha, made like the Oyl of Wine-ſtone, with the white of Eggs. Alſo
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59943:12"/> There is an Oyntment made of the Marrow of the Bones of a Weather, and is thus to be extracted.</p>
                  <p>Take of the bones of a Weather, (when 'tis full Moon) as much as you pleaſe, let them boil long in water, then break them in pieces. Let them boil again in the water three or four hours, then take them from the fire, and let them be cold; then gather the fat which will ſwim upon the the water, and Anoint your Face there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with at night when you go to bed, and the next morning. Waſh it off with the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Bean-Bloſſomes, or of Flower-de-luce.</p>
                  <p>Another Oyntment is made of Pige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons dung, and campher'd Roſe-water.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another Oyntment or Pomade.</head>
                  <p>Take Goats greaſe half a pound, freſh unmelted Hogs greaſe four ounces, cut in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſmall pieces; put it into a glazed ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then pot, with a Pippin cut in pieces, Juice of Orange, Roſe-water a glaſs-full, white-Wine half a glaſs-full; put the pot upon the fire, and let it boil a little. When the Greaſe is melted, and incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated with the Apple, ſtrain it through a Sive, or Serſe, into an earthen pot glaſed,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59943:12"/> and half full of freſh water. When it is cold, take it out, and waſh it five or ſix times in Roſe-water, every time renewing the water. To a Pomade.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another excellent Pomade.</head>
                  <p>Take Goats greaſe two ounces, Pip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pins two, Flower-de-luce Roots of Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence one ounce, a whole Lemmon; chop the greaſe, and cut the Apples and Roots in pieces. Add thereto, of the Marrow of a Weathers feet two ounces. Let it boil together in a ſufficient quantity of Roſe-water, in a glaſed pot, upon a gentle fire, until the Lemmon be conſumed, keeping the pot well covered. Then take it from the fire, and ſtrain that which is in the pot through a clean cloth; you muſt pound that which is gone through, and mix that which is preſſed out freſh, without fire, with the Oyl of Sweet Almonds. When it is mingled together, then waſh it with water of Bean-flowers, white Flower-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luce, Roſes, of each the like quantity. This being well mix'd, and made, you may keep in a glaſs well covered. With this excellent Pomade you may Anoint your Face at night, and waſh it off the next day in the morning with Rain-water.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:59943:13"/>
               <head>2. <hi>How to take away Sun-burning.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The Face may be preſerved from the burning of the Sun, and from Cold, by theſe following Salves and Medicines.</p>
               <p>Take Goats greaſe half a pound, being firſt waſhed in clear water; pound it in a little Morter, then boyl it in Roſe-water, and after ſtrain it through a fine cloth; with Oyl of Sweet Almonds one ounce, Sugar-Candy a quarter of an ounce, new white Wax as much as is enough. Boil all theſe in a glazed pot, over a ſoft fire, to the convenient thickneſs of a Salve, ſtirring it about continually, that it may become white, and be kept from burning. Being boiled, it muſt be kept in a Glaſs (cloſe ſtopped) for the uſe of a Salve.</p>
               <p>For the ſame uſe ſerveth alſo a Salve made with Maſtick, and with the Marrow of an Hart, or Ox. An Oyntment of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick with harſh Oyl, the water of the white of Eggs.</p>
               <p>A Pomade made with white wax, Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, and Oyl of Sweet Almonds, preſt out with fire; this Pomade takes away Sun-burning.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:59943:13"/>
               <head>3. <hi>How to take away Freckles and Spots.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take the Meal of Lupins, the Gall of a Goat, the Juyce of Lemons, and white Allum; mingle theſe to a Salve: Anoint therewith the Spots and Freckles.</p>
               <p>Or, mingle together the Oyl of Bitter Almonds, Honey, Roots of Flower-de-luce and Wax; then wet them with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Bean-flowers, Orange, and Mirtle.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another Salve to take away Freckles, Rubies and Saphires which appear in the Face.</head>
                  <p>Take water in which Rice hath been boiled, diſtilled water of Turpentine, with Oyl of Wine-ſtone, one ounce of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick, half a Loaf (that is, a quarter of an ounce) of Campher: mix theſe with the whites of Eggs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take diſtilled water of Radiſh-ſeed, and of great Spear-Root, (having been ſoaked before four days in the Sun in water,) ſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Oil of Egg-ſhels, Oil which is preſſed out of the Seed of Cotton-herb, the juice of the Root, and little Berries of Briony or wild Vine, the juice of Ladies-mark, with fig-bean-meal, (which is a kind of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59943:14"/> Pulſe, of an harſh and bitter taſt,) the freſh Flowers of Jaſmin, (being rubb'd in pieces upon the place of the diſtemper,) Pidgeons dung, being ſoaked in ſtrong Wine-vinegar, Meal of Fitches, and ſeed of the Herb Rocket, mingled with honey, oyl and water of Roſes, with freſh Butter, and Pignut-Roots, made to a Salve, Lentiles boyled ſoft, and mixed with the juice of Pomegranate.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>4. <hi>How to take wrinkles out of the Face and Hands, and to make them white.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take the Lees of Linſeed oyl, put it in Rain-water to ſoak.</p>
               <p>Or, take the juice of Lemons, and ſome corns of Salt, mixed together; waſh the wrinkles of the face and hands therewith.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>5. <hi>How to take away the Chops of the Lips and Hands.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take the white of an Egg, and beat it with the powder of Maſtick.</p>
               <p>Or, take the Oyl of the yolks of Eggs, or Oyl of Wax, and anoint therewith the Clefts or Chaps.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:59943:14"/>
               <head>6. <hi>How to make the Hands that are Yellow and Wrinkled, ſmooth and white.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take two pounds of Mellons, with their Skins or Rines, and a good quantity of Eggs without their ſhells: diſtil all this together, and keep the water, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to waſh your Hands, but your Face.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another ſmoothing Water.</head>
                  <p>Take Goats Milk ſix pounds, white or red Roſes, ſmall yellow Prunes, of each three pounds; crums of a white loaf, two pounds; Roots of Flower-de-luce, two ounces: diſtil theſe in hot water, through a glaſs.</p>
                  <p>Or, Boyl Roots of Nettles in Vineger and white-Wine; waſh your Hands with this Decoction at night when you go to bed, and the next morning waſh them clean with freſh water and ſoap.</p>
                  <p>Or, take freſh Butter, Oyl of Sweet Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, Lambs Suet; let theſe ſoak ten or twelve hours together, then melt them over a little fire, in a glazed earthen pot, adding thereunto white wax, with a little Musk or Civet: make this into a Salve.</p>
                  <p>Or ſometimes you may waſh your hands with ſweet-ſented water and ſoap, or with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:59943:15"/> ſtilled water of Bread, or with water and Rolls of bread. To theſe waters you may add ſweet-ſcented water, as water of Orange-flowers, Damask-water, or a little Oyl of Cloves, Cinnamon, or the like.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <head>7. <hi>How to take away Warts off the Face or Hands.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The juice of Lemmons killeth Warts, but better the water of the ſame juice, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilled through a glaſs. Or the juice which is preſſed out of the Flowers and Leaves of white Wool-blade.</p>
               <p>Alſo the juice of the Leaves of great Spear-herb. Alſo wart-Cicory, either ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in Sallets, or laid upon the face or hands, or other parts, cures the ſame to admiration.</p>
               <p>Alſo the Milky juice of Woolfs Milk, and that of the wild fig-tree, Oyl of Red Copper, or Spaniſh Green, Brimſtone, the greaſe which is gotten from the old Cask of an Oyl-Veſſel, made hot before a great fire, the juice that is pounded out of the ſprouts of Purſlane, (without the leaves) in a little Morter, adding thereunto a little Salt; this will cauſe the Warts to vaniſh away in four or five days, when they are anointed therewith.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:59943:15"/>
               <p> Or, lay on the Warts the Powder of Savil, or white-Daffadil (Hermodactyl) with Honey, Vineger, and Sea-Onion, mix'd with the juyce of Marigolds: ſheeps-dung ſoaked in Vineger, cureth hanging-Warts, being laid thereupon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="part">
               <head>8. <hi>To take away Blood-Veins in the Face.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Sometimes a Vein appears unhandſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly between the Eyes, for which it is good to lay on the fore-head this Plaiſter.</p>
               <p>Take Maſtick one ounce, Sandal-wood half an ounce, Margaret-flowers three quarters of an ounce; mix theſe together, and ſpread them upon Leather, with the fine filing duſt of Steel. Upon the Vein you ſhall onely lay Maſtick and Sandal-wood, renewing the Plaiſter once a day; rub alſo therewith the upper part of the Vein, for the better reception of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="part">
               <head>9. <hi>How to cure a Red Face.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Waſh it with water in which Chaff or ſtraw of Barley or Oats hath been boiled.</p>
               <p>Or, Peach-kirnels four ounces, peeled Gourd-ſeed two ounces; pound and preſs them ſo hard, that Oyl may come out of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:59943:16"/> them to the ſubſtance of an Ointment, anoint therewith the Pimples and red pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="part">
               <head>10. <hi>How to heal Burning and Bliſtering.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Againſt all burning and bliſtering occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by fire, make a Decoction of Radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, which lye on unquenched Lime.</p>
               <p>Or, take an Onion roaſted in the Aſhes: or, Oyl of Nuts with water: or, the yolks of Eggs beaten with Oyl: or, Hens-dung mixt with Oyl of Roſes.</p>
               <p>Or, the Moſs of an Haw-thorn-tree, the thinneſt you can get; dry it in the Sun or Oven, make a powder thereof, prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it with the Milk of a woman that giveth ſuck to a Male-child; make a Salve thereof, and anoint therewith the burnt place.</p>
               <p>Or, take ſalt-water or pickle, wet a lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen-cloth therein, and put it upon the burnt place.</p>
               <p>Or, take common Soap, Honey, and Butter, or juyce of Onyons, or Oyl of Eggs.</p>
               <p>Or, let Loam, red Copper, or Spaniſh-green, or Pellitory of the Wall, or Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, be ſteeped in wine and water; pour it often out of one pot into another, then
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59943:16"/> wet a cloth in this water, (that firſt is made luke-warm) and lay it upon the burnt place.</p>
               <p>Or, take the white of two Eggs, beat them with Oyl of Nuts and Roſe-water, adding thereto water wherein unquench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Lime hath been extinguiſhed; ſtir it well about, and let the water ſtand until you have occaſion for it. And to the end that no ſcar may remain after the burning is healed, you muſt waſh the burnt place often with Lambs-tongue-water, in which a little Allum is diſſolved.</p>
               <p>Or, you may uſe an Oyntment of hogs-bread Roots<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> pounded with Houſe-leek: but Brandy is better to waſh the Scars of the burnt place, whether they be in the face or other parts of the body.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="part">
               <head>11. <hi>How to cure the POX, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions thereof.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take water ten pints, quench therein rough iron, until the half be found in the water. Then lay therein to ſoak unquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched Lime one pound; ſtrain it, and melt in that which is gone through or ſtrained Campher, Spaniſh-green, Red-copper, of each twenty Grains. This water is good to cleanſe and dry the Ulcers.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:59943:17"/>
               <p> Or, boil clear water in a new earthen pot, and when it begins to boil, put there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in unquenched Lime; then put it out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another new pot; then let it ſtand: ſcum it till it be clear; the Lime will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in the bottom like a pap; then pour out the clear water, without ſtirring the Lime, and put it into a clean glaſs well ſtopped for uſe. In this water dip a little cloth, (the water being made luke-warm) and lay it upon the Ulcers inſtead of a Plaiſter, renewing it often.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="part">
               <head>12. <hi>To take away Pockholes, and make the skin ſmooth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take of the Oyl of St. Johns-herb one ounce, Venetian Turpentine half an ounce; melt it in a glazed pot, and as ſoon as it begins to boil, take it from the fire, and work it into a Salve; anoint therewith the ſcars and ſpots, continuing to do ſo till the holes be ſtopp'd.</p>
               <p>Or, take the ſtilled water of the white of Eggs, boyled hard with ſhells; of Snails, of Calves, of Weathers, of Goats-feet, of Bean-flour, Dragonwort, <hi>(i. e. Serpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taria.)</hi> Theſe waters you ſhall uſe ſingle, or mingled together, and with that bathe the face when you go to bed, having pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59943:17"/> the ſame with the ſteam or ſmoak of warm water: or, decoction of the chaff of Oats, Oyl of Dates, Flower-de-luce, Myrrha, (Piſtacies.)</p>
               <p>Or, take three Ounces of the Oyl of Flower-de-luce, Roſen, Capons-greaſe, of each one ounce; waſh them well in Roſe-water: add thereunto four whites of Eggs half boiled in their ſhells, Oyl of Sweet and Bitter Almonds planched, of each one ounce; pound them in a Marble Morter, mingling therewith a quarter of an ounce of the powder of Melon-ſeed; work it to a Salve.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the Powder of Silver-ſcum, burnt Bones of a Calf, dry Reed-Roots, bitter Almonds, Pompion or Melon-ſeed, Radiſh-ſeed, Meal of Rice, Beans, Fig-beans, (a kind of Pulſe of an harſh and bitter taſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) Turkiſh-beans, white-Cicory, of each as much as you ſhall think fit or convenient: diſſolve theſe in Roſe-water, and mix them to a Salve.</p>
                  <p>There is another Salve made with Oyl of Almonds and Brimſtone, with Aſſes greaſe, juyce of Reed-Roots and Honey; Roots of a white-Vine boil'd in the Oyl of Olives, the powder of a Crab-fiſh burnt, the Aſhes of Wine-ſtone, and of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59943:18"/> Myrrha; ſpread this Salve upon the face, being made wet with the ſteam or ſmoak of water. It is very uſeful to heal the ſcars and black-ſpots of the pox.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="part">
               <head>13. <hi>To take away Scabs and Scurff, which eat into the skin.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take the juice of Purſlain, Lambs-tongue, Night-ſhade, and Lemons; if this be not ſufficient, then add thereto red Wine-ſtone: apply this mixture to the place eaten in by the Scabs.</p>
               <p>Or, lay the Root of the Herb Patient a ſoaking for one day, in ſtrong wine-vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar; cut it in ſlices, and with one of the ſlices chafe the fore place three or four times a day.</p>
               <p>Or, take of Aloes half a quarter of an ounce, Sublimate ten grains, water of Lambs-tongue-leaves, Night-ſhade, (as much as you ſhall judge ſufficient) of each a like quantity; boil all theſe together, to the conſumption of the half, and work them to an Oyntment.</p>
               <p>Or, take Gum of the black-cherry-tree, a little Brimſtone, and twice as much Salt; put theſe to ſoak in ſtrong wine-Vineger, rub therewith the ſore place, or chafe it in with faſting ſpittle, or with the gum
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:59943:18"/> which runs out of the Vine; but firſt mix them with Salt-peter, and pounded To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco, <hi>(viz.</hi> the juice and herb pounded together.)</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="part">
               <head>14. <hi>To take away white Scabs and Sores.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Waſh the Patients head with Oxepipe, until it bleed, and then ſpread thereupon the Powder of the dung of a white hen, dryed in an Oven.</p>
               <p>Or, Soot of the Chimney bruiſed, and mixed with ſtrong Vineger.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="part">
               <head>15. <hi>How to prevent the falling of Hair, and to make Hair grow.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Rub the bare place with Red-cloth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til it bleed; then rub it with a Salve made of Honey, Flax-ſeed-Oyl, Powder of Gnats; roaſt theſe upon a Tile.</p>
               <p>Or, rub it with a Mouſe-turd and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, or with burnt Nut-ſhells, which are mixed with Wine and Oyl.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="part">
               <head>16. <hi>To make white or gray Hairs black.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take bruiſed Gall-nuts, fry them in an Iron-pan till they be very black, drop there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (by little and little) the Oyl of Olives,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59943:19"/> ſtirring it conſtantly till it be well incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated: hold them over the fire till it be dry, then bruiſe them to powder, adding there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Red-Copper, Roſemary, Chryſtal Salt, <hi>(Sal Gemmae)</hi> dryed clay, or Pot-earth, and Cloves pounded ſmall; this being done, take Allum, ſhells of Nuts and of Pomgranats, of each a like quantity; boil theſe in wine, until they be as black as Ink, then ſtrain them, and put the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Powder therein; but firſt, before you apply it to the Head, moiſten the Head with a very good Lye. Then waſh it with this Wine, and keep it covered five or ſix hours, then rinſe it with wine and water; then dry it, and the hair will continue black for five or ſix Months.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="part">
               <head>17. <hi>How to kill Nits.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Make a Decoction of the Lye of Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, Acorns, and Nuts, in ſtrong wine-Vineger.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="part">
               <head>18. <hi>How to kill Lice.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Chafe the place with the juice of brine, mix'd with the Oyl of Anis, or of Juni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, or with a Decoction of Lice-herb, <hi>(Staphiſagria.)</hi> Or boil Bacon in a Leaded-pot, and white Frankincenſe, of each a
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59943:19"/> like quantity, to the ſtifneſs of a Salve ſtrain it, and keep it for your uſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="part">
               <head>19. <hi>How to cure the ſtinging of venemous Beaſts.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>If a Mouſe, Spider, Fly, Waſp, Horſe-leech, or any venemous beaſt, by ſtinging or biting, have cauſed the fleſh to ſwell, then you ſhall ſtroke gently the place which is hurt, with the juice of Southern-wood, and the pain ſhall immediately ceaſe, and the ſwelling alſo will diminiſh.</p>
               <p>Or, lay thereupon the dung of an Ox or Cow hot, or ſmear it with faſting ſpittle.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="part">
               <head>20. <hi>A cure for the Head-ach.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>If it be occaſioned by heat, you ſhall lay thereupon little ſlices of Gourd, or a fine cloath dipt in Roſe-water, juice of Lambs-tongue, Night-ſhade, Lettice, or Purſlain put into white-Wine.</p>
               <p>Or, beat the white of two Eggs with Roſe-water, wet Tow in it, and lay it to the fore-head</p>
               <p>Or, waſh your head with luke-warm water, wherein wine and Sage-leaves have been boiled, or Roſes and Prune-flowers; with this Decoction waſh the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:59943:20"/> Legs and Feet. If the pains be ſo great that the underſtanding be prejudiced, then lay upon the top of the Head, fore-head, and Temples, a Poultis of the white of an Egg, <hi>Bolus Armenius,</hi> ſowre Apples boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; or in Betony-water and Wine-vineger: but if the pain proceedeth from Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, then make a ſmall cuſhion of Venus Hair and Roſes, and bind it about the fore-head: or you ſhall receive the vapour of boil'd Coleworts: or as ſoon as the Head begins to ake, eat one or two bitter Almonds: or drink grated Harts-horn in River or Fountain-water, or mix it with the hair of the dog that bit you.</p>
               <p>But if the Head-ach be occaſioned by cold, then lay upon the Head little bags filled with Barley, and roaſted-ſalt, Sage, Marjoram, Thyme, Annis, and bay-berries, Juniper-berries, as hot as you can endure it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="part">
               <head>21. <hi>How to cure inveterate Head-ach, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers of the Skull.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Roaſt in the aſhes a little piece of the uttermoſt rind of an Onion, wet and ſprinkled with the Oyl of Roſes, or Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel-berries; put it into the Ear, on that ſide the pain is: it is alſo neceſſary to keep
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:59943:20"/> a good Diet, without which, all Remedies are in vain. Therefore in all kind of Head-achs drink but little Wine, and eat but a little; let your Victuals be good, and ſuch as will feed little; as the fleſh of young Hens, Stewed Lettice, Purſlain and Sorrel, Milk of Sweet-Almonds, with peel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Barley: eat no windy Herbs, nor ſod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den-meat, nor Milk alone, which is very bad in this Diſtemper, and for all ſorts of Agues: let the Patient diſcharge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of all diſturbances of Mind, neither let him read nor write much, but with quietneſs expect by Gods Bleſſing the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of theſe means.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="part">
               <head>22. <hi>A Remedy againſt Madneſs.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>For the cure of Madneſs occaſioned by hot ſickneſſes, bind on the Head the Lungs or whole Pluck of a Weather newly killed, or a Chicken or Pigeon ſplit on the midſt of the back; put it on the Patients Head, or anoint the fore-head (eſpecially the Temples) with Oyl of Roſes, Vineger, and Poplar-ſalve, or with the juice of Night<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhade, Oyl of Roſes, and Wine-Vineger.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="part">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:59943:21"/>
               <head>23. <hi>A Cure for the Lethargy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Make a little cuſhion filled<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worts boiled in Vinegar, and bind it on the fore-head.</p>
               <p>Or, let the fume of ſtrong-Vinegar aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend into the Patients noſtrils.</p>
               <p>Or, the ſent of Rhue, and the ſeed of <hi>(Nigella)</hi> Partridge-feathers, old ſhoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patches, Aſs-claws, or mans hair, burnt.</p>
               <p>Or, bind on the fore-head a Plaiſter of Mithridate, and on the right Arm the Head of a Bat.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="part">
               <head>24. <hi>To procure Sleep.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Bind about the head a little cuſhion made of Lettice-ſeed, and juice of Night<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhade, or Womans Milk that gives ſuck to a Girl.</p>
               <p>Or, lay under the Pillowbere an Apple of Mandragora, or anoint the ſoles of the feet with the greaſe of a ſmall Weazel.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="part">
               <head>25. <hi>A Cure for the dizzineſs of the Head.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>If the Head be ſubject to giddineſs, take Aquavitae, Syrup of Gilliflowers, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of Anacardina.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="part">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:59943:21"/>
               <head>26. <hi>A Cure for the Falling-ſickneſs.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>To cure and preſerve from the Falling-ſickneſs, called alſo St. <hi>Johns</hi> Evil, drink for Nine days together about half a drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-glaſs of Petty-mullein, or Longwort, or the water of the flowers of a Sicca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more-tree, or Coriander, or the Powder of Piony-ſeed, five or ſix days together.</p>
               <p>Or, rub the Head with a little ſtone which is found in the neſt of a Swallow; or wear a Ring about the neck, or on the finger, in which the claw of an Elandt is incloſed; but let not the claw eat the fleſh of the neck or finger. Alſo it will be cured, if you tickle or nip the neck un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the great Tooth, or if you anoint their Lips with Mans Blood.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="part">
               <head>27. <hi>How to cure the Dead-Palſey.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>To cure and preſerve from the Dead-Palſey, drink in the winter a ſpoon-full of Aquavitae and Sugar, and then eat a piece of White-bread; or inſtead of Aqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitae, Taret-water, (which we ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe hereafter.)</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="part">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:59943:22"/>
               <head>28. <hi>How to cure the Apoplexy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Chaſe the afflicted places with Oyl of Bay-berries, and Beavers Wine; mingle therewith ſome Aquavitae; you may alſo uſe Cynnamon-water, or St. Johns Herb, or preſerved Sage, Roſemary, Field-Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, Balme, and Mithridate; make alſo dry-ſtewings, with a Decoction of Laven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Balſom, and Marjoram.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="part">
               <head>29. <hi>How to cure the Shaking-Palſey.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Drink for a great while, the Decoction of Field-Cypreſs, Petty-mallein, and Sage; eat alſo the kernels of Pine-Apples.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="part">
               <head>30. <hi>How to ſtrengthen weak Eyes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take Fenickle, the Herb Vervin, Eye-bright, Rhue, and Roſes, of each a little quantity; diſtil them, drop into the Eyes every morning and evening three or four drops of this water.</p>
               <p>Or, of the diſtilled water of Rotten-Apples; alſo 'tis good to receive the fume of the waters in which Fenile, Eye-bright and Rhue have been boiled; or to drink every morning half a glaſs of the wine of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59943:22"/> Eye-bright, or to prepare a Powder of dryed Eye-bright with Sugar; take there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of every morning two or three ſpoonfuls before you eat.</p>
               <p>There is a ſtone to be found in an Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall, which being put into the Noſtrils, will make the ſight very clear.</p>
               <p>Alſo you may uſe Wine in the morning, made of Stone-Rhue-Roots.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="part">
               <head>31. <hi>A Cure for the running of the Eyes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Lay a Plaiſter upon the fore-head made of Snail-ſlime, beaten with Frankincenſe and Aloes, till it be as thick as Honey.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="part">
               <head>32. <hi>A Cure for Weeping Eyes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>All humours which fall into the Eyes may be dryed up by a Decoction made of the leaves of Betony, Fenickle-root, and a little Frankincenſe; waſh the Eyes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</p>
               <p>Or, by a Decoction of Chervil; mix therewith the juice of Rue, with ſcum'd honey.</p>
               <p>Or, bind behind the head Rolls of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, which have a great virtue to hinder the humour or Rheum that falleth down the Throat.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:59943:23"/>
               <p> Or, drop into the Eyes the diſtilled wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a Mans Gall, and the Herb Salan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine.</p>
               <p>Or, anoint the corners of the Eyes with blacking, which is made of Butter burnt in a Lamp; this Remedy dryeth up all run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Eyes, and is convenient for all Running-ſores and Fiſtula's, which come of Humours and Rheums.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="part">
               <head>33. <hi>To cure the Redneſs or Inflammation of the Eyes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Lay a Linnen-cloth, or Tow of Flax, which is wet in the white of Eggs, and well beaten with Roſe or Lambs-tongue-water; or take a ſower rotten-Apple, mingled with womans-Milk, and anoint therewith the Eye-lids.</p>
               <p>Or, make a Garland of Damask-Roſes, or the Preſerve of Roſes, and other things drawing together; lay theſe upon the Temples of the Head, and they will hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the humour which occaſions the redneſs.</p>
               <p>Or, ſoak in Womans-Milk little ſlices of Veal, or of the neck of an Ox newly kill'd; lay them upon the Eyes, and Tow upon them.</p>
               <p>Or, take the Urine of a young Child;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:59943:23"/> take it in a Copper Veſſel or Metal; let it ſtand covered with a fine cloath twenty four hours: of this gather together the Ruſt, and mingle it with Roſe-water; put it into a glaſs with a narrow neck, ſtop it well, and drop ſome of it into the Eyes in the morning and at night, or prepared Tutty.</p>
               <p>But againſt the inveterate redneſs of the Eyes, take white Copperas, to the bigneſs of a ſmall Nut bruiſed, (there are ſeveral ſorts of Flowers ſo called) white Allum, of each the twenty fourth part of an ounce, Fountain-water one pint: mingle theſe together to an Eye-water, or boil them together until the water be clear; drop three or four drops of this into the Eyes: or, make a Plaiſter of Leaven, or of the remainder of Flax-ſeed Oyl, Gum of Arabia-Dragant, Maſtick, and Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="part">
               <head>34. <hi>To cure the Inflammation of the Eyes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take the Lungs of a Weather newly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ill'd, (or of an Ewe) lay it upon the Eyes: or, take the pap of a ſweet roaſted-apple, mix it with Barley-meal, Womans-milk, Roſe-water, and white of Eggs.</p>
               <p>Or, water of Marygolds, the Eye of a
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:59943:24"/> Wolf; or the little ſtones which are found in the bellies of Swallows, being hung about the neck, have the ſame virtue.</p>
               <p>Or, take a piece of Frankincenſe upon the point of a ſtick, ſet it on fire with a wax-candle, extinguiſh it in four ounces of Roſe-water; continue the lighting and extinguiſhing thereof thirty times, then ſtrain it through a clean cloth to an Eye-water; drop ſome of it into the corners of the Eyes at night when you go to bed, and if you pleaſe, mingle with the water ſome womans Milk.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="part">
               <head>35. <hi>To take red Spots out of the Eyes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Make a Plaiſter of green-wormwood pounded in a womans Milk and Roſe-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Or, drop into the Eyes the blood of the wing of a Pigeon or Turtle-dove; this laſt is good when the Eye is hurt with a blow.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="part">
               <head>36. <hi>To cleanſe the Eyes of Matter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Wipe them, and ſtroak them gently with a Saphire wet in cold water.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="part">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:59943:24"/>
               <head>37. <hi>To take Spots and Webs out of the Eyes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take the new-laid Eggs of a black Hen, roaſt them hard in hot aſhes, cut them in four equal parts, take out the yolks, fill them with white-ſugar-candy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ruiſed, then ſtrain them through a clean <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>innen-cloth very hard; this water or Oyl <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s good to drop into Eyes, at any time of the day or night.</p>
               <p>Or, you may make a water of white-Coperas, Sugar-candy, Roſe-water, and the white of Eggs hard-boyled; ſtrain theſe through a linnen-cloth, drop this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the Eyes at noon, after dinner, and at light when you go to bed. Alſo the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>owder of white-beans onely put into the Eyes, is very good.</p>
               <p>Or, take prepared Tutty ſcrap'd ſmall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne ounce, Broad-ſword half an ounce; ſoak his in Roſe-water and white-wine, of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ach about one pint; let it ſtand ſix weeks together in the Sun, in a well-ſtopp'd-glaſs, when the Sun ſhines bright, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ake it away when it ſhineth not; ſtir the glaſs twice or thrice a day, to an Eye-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alve. Theſe Remedies alſo ſerve againſt Red and Blear'd-eyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="part">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:59943:25"/>
               <head>38. <hi>To take away the pain of the Eyes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Make a Decoction of Camomile, Mel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lot, and Fenickle-ſeed, boil theſe in water and white-wine, dip therein a four-doub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> cloth, wring it hard, and apply it to the Eyes: or, bath the Eyes in womans Milk, beaten with the white of an Egg.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="part">
               <head>39. <hi>To cure the pain of the Ears.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>If it proceeds from an hot cauſe, tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Oyl of Roſes, with a little Vinegar; ſpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> them into the Ears, and lay thereon a ſmall bag of Camomile, Melilot, Flax<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>ſeed boiled in Milk: but if the pain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> occaſioned by Inflammation, then take th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> blacking of the ſmoak of boyled pitch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> mingle it with a little Oyl of Roſes, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pour it warm into the Ears: if the pai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be occaſioned by cold, put into the E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Cotten, made ſweet with one grain o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Musk.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="part">
               <head>40. <hi>To help thickneſs of Hearing.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Drop into the Ears the juyce of a wild-vine, or of Onion mingled with Honey o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Oyl, wherein Affodel-roots have been boi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="part">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:59943:25"/>
               <head>41. <hi>A Cure for Deafneſs.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Make a Salve of the following Ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents; take Gooſe-greaſe two ounces, melt it over a ſoft fire, mingling with it pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Aloes half an ounce; this you ſhall put into the Ears with Cotton: or take the juice of Radiſh-skins, mingled with Oyl of Roſes, or the fat of an Eel, with Oyl of bitter Almonds, or the juyce of an Onion mingled with Honey, or Powder of Aloes diſſolved in white-wine, and dropped warm into the Ear. Then to ſneeze with the Root of Hellebore, or let the fume of Aſh-wood be received into the Ear, which you may do, by firing a ſtick of Aſh-wood at the one end, and putting the other end to the hole of the Ear, into which the ſmoak will eaſily enter: the ſtick muſt be of a young ſhoot without knots. This is of great virtue for the cure of Deafneſs, although it be of 25 or 30 years; but againſt natural Deafneſs there is no remedy.</p>
               <p>Or, take Wormwood, Cammomile, Thouſand-leaf, Hyſop, St. Johns Herb, Fine-mint, Roſemary, Saintory, Savory, of each one handful; boil theſe in white-wine, to the conſumption of one third
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59943:26"/> part thereof, and let the hot ſmoak into the Ear through a Funnel, and then drop ſome of the following Oyl into the Ear, and ſtop the Ear with Cotton in which Musk hath been.</p>
               <p>Or, take Oyl of Olive two ounces, Mallows one ounce and a half, Oyl of Oni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſweet Almonds, of each one ounce; put all theſe together into a flask with a long neck, ſet it on a fire that is not too hot, boil them until the juices be half con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed; then take the duſt hence, and put therein powdred Caſtoreum, Coloquint, Maſtick, Spikenard, of each the ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth part of an ounce; then take the flask, and being well ſtopt, boil it in a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle kettle full of water (like a <hi>Balneum Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae)</hi> for three hours; then put it in the Sun a little while, to cauſe the Oyl to be clear; then ſtrain the Oyl through a thick cloath, and add thereunto Musk ten grains, to an Oyl; keep it ſafe and carefully in a well-ſtop'd flask for uſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="part">
               <head>42. <hi>A Cure for the Worms in the Ears.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take the Milky juyce of a Fig-tree or Figgs, alſo the juyce of Capers, Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, Futher-wood, Fine-mint, Santory, the rind of an Acorn-tree, or the rind of green Acorns alone, or mingled together.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="part">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:59943:26"/>
               <head>43. <hi>A Cure for the noiſe in the Ears.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Drop therein Oyl of Spikenard, Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berries, Bitter-Almonds, or of Rhue, with ſome Brandy, or Eels-greaſe, or Brandy where Carraway or Anniſeed have been ſoaked.</p>
               <p>Or, take Saw-duſt of Cedar-wood, fill therewith a little Taffata-bag of Crimſon, as big as an Almond; let it ſoak in Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy quite through, then put it ſomewhat deep into the Ear, ſtop it in, and let the Patient lye down to ſleep on that Ear.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="part">
               <head>44. <hi>To take away little <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers from behind the Ears.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Make a Plaiſter of Barley-meal boiled in Honey-water, add thereto the juyce of five-leaved-graſs (an Herb that killeth fleas) and Oyl of Flower-de-luce, or a Plaiſter made of Goats-dung, unſalted Butter, and the Lees of Nut-oyl.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="part">
               <head>45. <hi>Againſt the Kings Evil.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take Betony and Sorrel-leaves and Roots, ſqueeze out one pound of the juyce, and Bertram bruiſed one ounce, Spaniſh-green
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59943:27"/> half a quarter of an ounce: mingle theſe together, and warm therewith the Crop or Swelling; hang alſo about the neck, the Roots of Selandine and Lambs-tongue.</p>
               <p>Or, when the Moon decreaſeth, and is near the Sun, then cut off the feet of a great frog, and hang them about the neck.</p>
               <p>Or, take a good quantity of Tobacco, bruiſed in a clean Morter, and apply its juyce to the Crop or Swelling nine or ten times: the ſaid ſwellings are brought to Ulcers, by laying thereunto Cow or Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dung, made hot in Vine or Colewort-leaves, among the aſhes, and being ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with Vineger.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="part">
               <head>46. <hi>A Remedy for the ſtopping of the Noſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>When the Noſe is ſtopped by humours that fall into it, and hinder the fetching of breath, then to open the ſame, take the juyce of Beets and Marjoram, mingled with the Oyl of bitter-Almonds, and ſnuff it up.</p>
               <p>Alſo the ſmoak of Tobacco, received into the mouth through a little Funnel, and let go through the Noſe, is good alone.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="part">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:59943:27"/>
               <head>47. <hi>For a dropping Noſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>This is cured by Medicines which are proper for the brains, whereby ſuch hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours are ſtopp'd and dried up. In this caſe 'tis good to uſe Rubbings, Perfumes, in little caps and bags; alſo ſneezing is very good.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="part">
               <head>48. <hi>To procure Sneezing.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Blow into the Noſe powdered Peper, Berthram, <hi>(Staphiſagria)</hi> Flower-de-luce Roots of Florence; mingle theſe flowers and greaſe, and anoint the Noſtrils: if ſneezing trouble you, it is cured by ſcratch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſoles of the feet, and palms of the hands, by rubbing the Eyes and Ears, by ſmelling white Flower-de-luce, by waſhing or bathing the hands in warm-water.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="part">
               <head>49. <hi>To recover the Smelling when 'tis loſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Make a Perſume of Nardus-ſeed, Ave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rone, Rhue, and other Herbs which have a ſtrong ſent; or ſmell to water-Mint.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="part">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:59943:28"/>
               <head>50. <hi>To ſtaunch Blood.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>You may ſtanch the bleeding of the Noſe, by putting the Thumb on that ſide of the Noſe out of which the blood iſſueth.</p>
               <p>Or, put about the neck a ſtring of Jaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-ſtone, or tye the uppermoſt joints as faſt as 'tis poſſible, and put into the Noſe a Tent of Dove-nettles; alſo keep in your hand the Roots and Leaves of Agrimony; or take rain-water in your Mouth, or Sage-flower, or other woolly fruits being put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Noſe; or lay upon the forehead Camphire, or uſe the juyce of Lambs-tongue, or of Night-ſhade.</p>
               <p>Or, lay upon the Temples and round about the neck, (eſpecially on the great Vein) cooling herbs, as Night-ſhade, Lambs-tongue, Lactuce, or ſtinging nettles, brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with Salt and wine-venegar; the Herb Periwinckle put under the Tongue, hath the ſame virtue.</p>
               <p>Alſo you may make a Girdle or Bracelet of Thouſand-button, called St. Innocentius; ſome hold a white-Mallow on the ſide of the bleeding noſtril; Many Coutrymen ſtench all ſorts of bleeding, in what part of the body ſoever.</p>
               <p>With Hogs-dung wrap'd up in Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, and put it to the place that bleeds: or, blow into the Noſe the powder of a
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:59943:28"/> three-cornered ſtone which is found in the of a Carp.</p>
               <p>Againſt too much bleeding at the Noſe, the Powder of Sandarica is very good, beaten with the white of an Egg, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aid upon the fore-head with a cloath.</p>
               <p>Alſo the juyce of Onion and Wine-vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar put into the Noſtrils with a little cloth, or the water of Mint drunk, or red-Coral drunk with Wine; or to anoint the fore-head with a Salve made of Dragon-blood, Maſtick, Frankincenſe, and the whites of Eggs mingled together. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rariwiſe, you may cauſe the Noſe to bleed with a ſheaf of corn, or Thouſand-leaf, when you put the ſharp end into the Noſe before the herb; and the contrary cometh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o paſs when you put the ſtump or end <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat is cut off in firſt: ſuch various man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers of the uſe of things, often bring forth divers cures.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="part">
               <p>1. <hi>To cure Biles and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers in the Noſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take the juyce of Veyl, and of ſower Pomegranates, and mingle them together.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="part">
               <head>52. <hi>Againſt the ſtinking of the Noſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Snuff up the Decoction of Marjoram,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:59943:29"/> fine-Mint, Cloves, Ginger and Musk, and boil them in whine-wine or vineger: of Sea-Onyon, <hi>(Acetum Squilliticon.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Or, uſe Sirrups, as of Diacodium, and the like: or hold in your mouth little Pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets of Bolus Armenius, Sealed Earth, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſtone, Dragon-blood, Cloves, and Musk.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="part">
               <head>53. <hi>A Remedy for a ſtinking Mouth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Waſh it with Wine wherein is boiled Anniſeed and Cloves; alſo Musk, Maſtick, of blew Flower-de-luce Root.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="part">
               <head>54. <hi>To Cure <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers and Sores in the Mouth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Rinſe it with a Decoction of the leaves of Nail-herb, <hi>(Peloſella,)</hi> Welch-root, Golden-Rod, or the flowers of wild Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>granates, Lambs-tongue, Agrimony, and Roſes; adding thereto ſome Allum, with wine in which Annis and Gilleflowers have been boiled, or with ſtilled water of Harts-tongue, or with Treacle-water, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilled with the like quantity of Roſemary and Brandy; among which, a little Bolus Armenius muſt be broken. The Decocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Hen-peaſe, <hi>(Elatina)</hi> of Piloſella made with wine, and gargled, dryeth the Soars of the Mouth, and takes away
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:59943:29"/> the rawneſs of the Tongue which comes by an Ague.</p>
               <p>Alſo it is a ſingular Remedy to touch the Ulcers with a drop of the Oyl of Copperas, or to anoint the ulcerating place in the Pallate of the Mouth, or on the Tongue, with Oyl of Roſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="part">
               <head>55. <hi>Of the Cure of exceſſive Slabbering.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>It is cured by Gargle-waters, that are drying and drawing together, made with the Decoction of Roſes, Flowers of wild-granats, Lambs-tongue, and Allum boiled in water and wine. 'Tis alſo good to eat Biskets, Roaſted meat with Muſtard, to chaw a Raſe of Ginger, and to drink good wine. But ſlabbering is excited with Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, dry Figs, or with Maſtick held in the Mouth in the morning faſting.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="part">
               <head>56. <hi>How to cleanſe the Teeth, and keep them ſound.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of filthy Teeth.</head>
                  <p>The Teeth being uſeful Inſtruments, ought eſpecially to be preſerved clean and faſt: brown and black Teeth ſhould be kept white, and looſe Teeth faſtned,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:59943:30"/> to the end they may be clean, without pain, and ſerviceable: the fitteſt time for this work is in the morning.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>How to Cleanſe the Teeth.</head>
                  <p>You ſhould rub your Teeth and whole Mouth and Gums, the Pallate and Tongue, with a clean courſe cloth, rubbing off the ſlime which groweth upon them in the night.</p>
                  <p>When you waſh your hands, you ſhould rinſe your Teeth with freſh-water that is not too cold, (if the Teeth be weak.)</p>
                  <p>Then you ſhall make them faſt, clean, and white, with theſe following Powders, with which you ſhall rub not onely the Teeth but the Gums, and then rinſe them with Red-wine.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>How to order your Teeth before Dinner or Supper.</head>
                  <p>The waters you ſhall uſe in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and at noon; for before you go to dinner, you ſhall rinſe the Teeth with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not too warm nor too cold, to cleanſe the Gums from the humours which fall down from the Brain, that in eating they mix not with your Meat. Fleſh or ſpoon-meat
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:59943:30"/> being eaten, or ſoopt too hot, is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry noxious to the Teeth; ſo is wine and water drunk too cold, (although many take delight therein in Summer.)</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>After Dinner or Supper.</head>
                  <p>After you have eaten and drank warm meat and drink, you muſt not immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately eat or drink any thing that is cold; nor on the contrary, when you have eaten any thing that is cold, you are not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to eat that which is very hot, but uſe a moderation between both.</p>
                  <p>Hard Meats are noxious to the Teeth; therefore 'tis beſt to eat ſuch meat as is tender, leſt you break your Teeth, or loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen them: you ſhould therefore forbear to break any hard thing with your Teeth; nay, not to bite a thin thread a ſunder.</p>
                  <p>Other qualities of Meats are likewiſe to be conſidered: for fat and lean, ſweet and ſowre things being too much uſed, are hurtful to the Teeth.</p>
                  <p>Phyſicians alſo obſerve, that husked or peaſcod Fruits, Milk-meat, Cheeſe, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, Sweet-meats, Tarts, Radiſhes, Figs, and moſt Orchard-fruits when they are raw, alſo Oyls and Fat, make the Teeth black.</p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:59943:31"/>
                  <p> Nevertheleſs, you need not, (but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to diſcretion) abſtain from all theſe Meats; but from thoſe which do moſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion the diſtempers of the Teeth where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with your are troubled.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of Pickt-Teeth.</head>
                  <p>After dinner or Supper, you ſhall rinſe your Teeth with Water mix'd with a little wine-vinegar, or with clear Wine. After you have cleared your Teeth of Meats which ſtick to them, this muſt be done ſoftly, with Tooth-picks not made of any Mettal; nay, not of Gold or Silver, but of wood, which hath ſome virtue of draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together, and are of a good ſmell: as of Maſtick-wood, Roſe-wood, Cypreſs, Roſemary, Myrtle-tree, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Next, rub your Teeth with Powders, which will keep them good, white, and clean: As of Myrrh, Cinnamon, burnt-Allum, burnt Pumice-ſtone, of each a like quantity; each being pounded ſmall apart, and after mingled together.</p>
                  <p>Crums of bread with common Salt, is very uſeful to rub the Teeth therewith af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Meals, and then to rinſe them with clean water mix'd with a little vineger, or with Red-wine, this will faſten the Teeth in the Gums.</p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:59943:31"/>
                  <p> There are divers other things, whereof Powders may be made to cleanſe the Teeth and make them white, of which ſome ſerve to comfort the Gums and make them grow when they are eaten off, for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of the Teeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Cauſes of the Tooth-ach.</head>
                  <p>And other Powders are good to cure the Tooth-ach, which is variouſly occaſioned; as being hollow, corrupted, full of worms, and from other cauſes. The Medicines which ſerve for this purpoſe are theſe.</p>
                  <p>Take Pearls, red and white Corals, Ivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Chryſtal, white-marble-ſtone, Alabaſter, Bertram, Hellebore, Harts-horn, Maſtick, Sea-ſcum, or Fiſh-bone, good Wine-ſtone, white-Copperas, ſtone-Salt, <hi>(Salgemmae)</hi> Crabs-eyes, Egg-ſhells, Snail-ſhells, Oyſter-ſhells, dry Roſes, the Root of Flower-de-luce, wild-Caliga, Venus-hair, burnt-wheat, and Barley-bread, Thamaris, Spica-Nardi, Dragon-blood, Roots of Harts-tongue, Flowers of wild Pomgranats, Cinnamon, and Cloves. All theſe you ſhall reduce into fine Powder, each apart, to joyn them together as neceſſity requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth.</p>
                  <p>Alſo Oyl and water of Copperas make
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:59943:32"/> the Teeth white; But ſome allow not of this, becauſe of their burning heat, and becauſe they imagine they will looſe the Teeth.</p>
                  <p>Indeed the water may better be uſed than the Oyl, and with leſs danger, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when you mingle it with common water, and rub the Teeth and Gums with it a Month together.</p>
                  <p>Of the afore-ſaid (and other like) In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients, a Powder may be made, and uſed very uſeful for the Teeth, with which you may rub them in the morning faſting.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Powder for the Teeth.</head>
                  <p>Take the Powder of clean Cryſtal one eighth part, and one ſixteenth part of an ounce, red and white Coral, of common Salt, of each the eighth part of an ounce; Pumice-ſtone, Sea-ſcum, of each the two and thirtieth part of an ounce; Alabaſter-ſtone, white Marble-ſtone, Rock-Allum, Root of Flower-de-luce of Florence, Crimſon-ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Cinnamon, of each the ſixteenth part of an ounce; prepared Pearls, the twenty fourth part of an ounce: make all theſe into a fine Powder (mingled together.)</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:59943:32"/>
                  <head>Preſerves for the Teeth.</head>
                  <p>Of ſuch Powders you may make Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, if you put honey thereto, with which you may rub your Teeth and Gums in the morning.</p>
                  <p>Another Preſerve may be made to make the Teeth white and faſt, and the Gums hard and ſtrong, which will alſo cure a ſtinking breath, proceeding from the Teeth, and 'tis thus prepared.</p>
                  <p>Take of a wheaten-loaf three ounces, red and white Coral, Harts-horn, of each half an ounce, Allum one ſixteenth part of an ounce, Pellitory of the wall, Venus-hair, of each one handful, Egg-ſhells four or five; put theſe together in an earthen-pot, ſet it in the Oven when the Bread is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out, till they be turned into aſhes; then take of theſe aſhes four ounces of Cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon the 4th part of an ounce, of Cloves or Gilliflowers, Bread-ſword, of each the eighth part of an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Spica-Nardi, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamus, of each the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>enth part of an ounce, well cleanſed Oyl of Roſes, as much as will be neceſſary; mingle the aforeſaid Ingredients, being reduced to a Powder) and add thereto vineger of Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onion one ounce; work this into a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve:
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:59943:33"/> when you have rubb'd the Teeth with theſe Preſerves, then rinſe them with wine.</p>
                  <p>With the aforeſaid Ingredients you may make very uſeful waters to rinſe the Teeth in the morning faſting.</p>
                  <p>As, take wild Mulberries when they are green one pound, leaves of the Maſtick-tree half a pound, Agrimony one handful, Roots of Flower-de-luce, Dragon-blood, of each three ounces: diſtil theſe through a glaſs, to a Tooth-water, and keep it in a glaſs for your uſe.</p>
                  <p>The following water is much commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for keeping the Teeth white.</p>
                  <p>Take Roſe-water and common-water, of each four ounces, burnt Allum powde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red one quarter of an ounce, whole Cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon the eighth part of an ounce; put all theſe together upon a ſoft fire, and let it boil until a third part thereof be conſumed; take it off then, and when the water is cold, ſtrain it through a cloth; put it into a glaſs, and keep it for your uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A Water to make Black Teeth White.</head>
                  <p>This following water cleanſeth the Teeth, how filthy and ſlimy ſoever, and makes Black Teeth White.</p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:59943:33"/>
                  <p> Take Live-brimſtone, and Allum, of each one pound, Wine-vineger four ounces (ſome take inſtead of vineger) the Spirit of Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peras; draw water out of theſe through a Colb-glaſs, with a ſlow fire, that the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter may not ſmell of the Brimſtone.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>For to make the Teeth White.</head>
                  <p>For to make the Teeth White, it is good alſo to rub the Teeth with Pellitory of the Wall, Roots of Beets, cruſt of bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley-bread, Goats-horn burned to aſhes; you may put all theſe things into an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then pot, and put it into the Oven with ſeveral Batches of Bread, till they become aſhes: or rub your Teeth with honey and aſhes of Vine-leaves which have not born any Grapes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>To preſerve the Teeth from filthineſs.</head>
                  <p>For to keep the Teeth clean, and to preſerve them from all filthineſs, waſh the Mouth every morning and evening with Fountain-water one pint, Roſe-water ſix ounces, Allum, Cinnamon, of each a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an ounce: boil this in a leaded ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then-pot, until one third or fourth part is conſumed.</p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:59943:34"/>
                  <p> Or, waſh the Teeth with Sage, Roſema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Marjoram, prepared with white-wine, and the ſame boil'd until two third parts are waſted.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="part">
               <head>57. <hi>How to faſten the Teeth when looſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>It is good to waſh the ſame with Roſe-water and Allum mixt together: or, the Roots of five-finger-graſs, and Allum.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="part">
               <head>58. <hi>For to prevent hollowneſs of the Teeth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Hold in the morning under your tongue, a courſe large corn of Bay-ſalt, let it melt, and rub your Teeth therewith. After that you have uſed all Remedies, it will be good for the preſervation of the Teeth, to rub them oftentimes with Roots of Marſh-Mallo's, by which means they will be ſmooth and bright: theſe Roots are eſpecially uſeful, for they make the gums faſt, and leave a good ſmell behind. When you prepare them, you ſhall cut the Roots off four or five fingers long; if they are groſs and thick, then you ſhall cut them through again in the length, for to make thereof pieces that are of the thickneſs of a little finger: next you ſhall let them boil ſix hours in clean water, with Salt,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:59943:34"/> Allum, and root of Flower-de-luce; at laſt you ſhall dry them, which muſt be done quickly, and not ſlowly, leſt they rot; therefore you ſhall put them in a hot Oven if it be in winter-time, when you cannot have the benefit of the Sun.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="part">
               <head>59. <hi>A Remedy againſt Tooth-ach.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The Tooth-ach proceeds from divers as well cold as hot cauſes; in caſe it is occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by cold, then uſe theſe following means.</p>
               <p>You ſhall rinſe the Teeth with ſtrong vinegar, in which Wormwood is boyl'd; Strawberries, or red-wine, in which are boyl'd leaves of Strawberries, with La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vender, Sage, and Marjoram; or White-Wine wherein the leaves and Nots of the Cypreſs-tree, Juniper-berries, and Roſes, Mirtle-leaves, are boiled; or the Flowers of Lavender, Cinamon, Fenickle, Roots of Sparagus boiled in Wine: oyl of Juniper-tree is good being put in the Teeth if they are hollow; but this following is better.</p>
               <p>Oyl of Pepper, Cloves, Sage, Bame, Oyl of Spike and Aqua-fortis, being gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put into the hollow Tooth with Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, takes away the pain, and breaketh it if it is corrupted.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:59943:35"/>
               <p> If the Tooth-ach proceeds from an hot cauſe, then you ſhall put to the painful Teeth Oyl of Poppeys, Mandragora, Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bane-ſeed, together or alone; or in want of oyls, the Mandragora and Henbane mixt with Wine; or Henbane Roots mixt with Roſe-water and Wine-vineger; or you ſhall hold in the Mouth Wine-vineger wherein Campher has been boiled: from what cauſe ſoever the Tooth-ach proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, you ſhall appeaſe the pain with Oyl of Henbane-ſeed, which is made after this manner: ſprinkle the ſeed of Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bane with Brandy, then put it into a glaſs, which you ſhall cover very cloſe, put it in a kittle full of water, and let it boil four and twenty hours; then take the glaſs out of the water, and put the ſeed before 'tis cold into a little linnen bag, and then preſs out the Oyl.</p>
               <p>This pain is alſo helped with the Roots of Thouſand-leaf, or of Agrimony, being held between the Teeth: and the ſame operation has the Root of Bertram <hi>(Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retrum.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Likewiſe againſt the Tooth-ach, you may boil the Root of Henbane, or of Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berries, in vineger and Roſe-water, and hold the water in the Mouth: or take a head of Garlick, let it roaſt in the hot
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:59943:35"/> aſhes; then bruiſe it, and put it as hot as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ver is poſſible to the Teeth, and put ſome of it into the Ear, on the ſide where the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ain is neareſt. Some bruiſe a head of Garlick, and put it upon the Artery or great Vein of the Arm, on the painful ſide.</p>
               <p>Or take Bertram bruiſed, (one quarter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f an ounce) Roſemary, Sage, of each <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne handful, large Figs, to the number of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hree; let theſe boil in half a pint of wine, until the Wine is all conſumed; then lay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne of theſe Figs upon the painful Tooth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s hot as you can bear it.</p>
               <p>Or, put very hot upon the Temples of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Head, a plaiſter of Pitch, beaten Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uts and Allum: it is good alſo to lay upon the Teeth the juyce of Garlick, Rue, Tanſie, <hi>(Matricaria)</hi> or any hot Oyl, as of Sage, which is excellent on this occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; or waſh and rinſe oftentimes your Teeth with a Decoction of Pennyroyal boiled in Wine, till two third parts are conſumed. Some hold for a ſecret, that a Tooth of a Man wrapt up in Taffeta, or a Bean with a hole, in which a Louſe is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hut up, being hanged about the neck, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd that theſe driveth away the greateſt Tooth-ach that can be.</p>
               <p>Great care has always been taken to drive away heavy and intollerable Tooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ach,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:59943:36"/> and to preſerve the Teeth, becauſe of the neceſſity of their ſervice; for which two things the moſt choiceſt means have been ſearcht for; inſomuch, that if the Proverb be made true in this point, that Neceſſity is the Mother of Arts, I have amongſt many innumerable means or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies which are found for the Teeth, brought forth a ſmall number, as being the choiceſt and moſt approved: and when all theſe Remedies will not help you, and that there is not any more hope of being delivered from the pain, then you muſt draw them. Sometimes the Teeth are ſpoiled becauſe of the putrefaction, but you muſt not inconſiderately begin this, but firſt conſult about it well, and then employ thereto a man that has skill there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, for fear of the many dangerous Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptomes, which are many times occaſioned thereby, when by a miſchance the good Tooth is taken for the bad, or that it is drawn out with too great force, whereby the blood runs out in abundance, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that the Patient runneth the hazard of his life: it were rather to be wiſht, that the corrupted Tooth might fall out through any other means, than by force: but the difficulty lyes in the finding out of thoſe things which have ſuch a proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and vertue.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:59943:36"/>
               <p> Some have uſed to put into the holes and hollowneſs of the Teeth, the aſhes of earth-worms, or mice-turd, or of the Tooth of a Hart, and theſe aſhes ſhall cauſe the Tooth to fall out immediately: or they put thereupon Mulberry-kernels, or put a ſoaking fifteen days in ſtrong Wine-vinegar, beaten Mulberry-Roots; after the ſoaking, the ſame being dryed in the Sun, they make a Powder thereof, to put it on the Tooth; or put thereon the brains of a Partridge, or the juyce of Cherry-leaves; or put into the hollowneſs of the Tooth the juyce of the Herb Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landine, and ſtrong-water.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="part">
               <head>60. <hi>Of Teeth ſet an edge.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The Teeth grow blunt by ſharp or ſowr victuals, eſpecially ſuch as are of a bad qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, <hi>viz.</hi> green, ſowr, and unripe fruit, whoſe roots are full of ſowr and tart juyce, as well as becauſe of vapours which climb out of the ſtomach unto the Teeth: for to be rid of this trouble, it is good to eat old and ſtrong Cheeſe, or Nuts, or Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, or to rub the Teeth with the like: or alſo by holding of Purſlain, or a Decoction of it in the Mouth: or to hold in the Mouth the Milk of an Aſs: or by rubbing the Mouth with Wine, after that
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:59943:37"/> you have rubbed the Teeth with Salt and Sage.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="part">
               <head>61. <hi>A Cure for a ſtinking Breath.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>For to cure a ſtinking breath, (from what cauſe ſoever it proceed) it is good to waſh the Mouth with vineger of Sea-onion, or with the Decoction of the leaves of Mint, the Herb Baulm, Sow-thiſtle, Roots of Flower-de-luce, of wild Galiga, Annis-ſeed, Fenickle-ſeed, and Paradiſe-corn; to gnaw Nutmegs, Flower-de-luce Roots, Clove-Gilliflowers, or to hold in the Mouth a little Pill, which is made after this manner.</p>
               <p>Take Gum-dragant one ounce, Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons blood half an ounce; let it ſoak two days in Roſe-water, and then add there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, in a little ſtone-morter, Sugar an ounce and a quarter, Cinnamon three eight parts of an ounce, Musk one ſcruple; this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pounded with a Peſtle in Roſe-water, and it being dryed, make it for uſe to ſmall Pills.</p>
               <p>The bad ſent occaſioned by the eating of Garlick, Onion, or Leeks, goes away by gnawing freſh Nuts, or leaves of Rue, of Fenickle, or Parſley.</p>
               <p>For to make the breath ſmell ſweet,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:59943:37"/> when it ſents not, it will be neceſſary to rinſe the mouth the Morning before with Cinnamon-water, and to hold the ſame a little while in the mouth, or with the water called <hi>Aqua Imperialis,</hi> or with Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle-water, or to uſe the Roots of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-wort, or of Flower-de-luce, or of Angelica or Maſtick.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="62" type="part">
               <head>62. <hi>A Cure for the Squinancy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Againſt Squinancies, make a Poultis of a whole Swallow-neſt, boiled in White-Wine, and then mingle it with Oyl of Cammomile and ſweet Almonds, and put it outwardly upon the Throat; or drink im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately water of <hi>Carduus Benedictus,</hi> with one eighth part of an ounce of the powder of a Boars tooth; or anoint the place with a Salve of Lint-ſeed-oyl and the fore-going Powder; or put thereupon a Pultis of the Turd of a young ſound youth or ſtrippling, who has been nouriſhed for three days together onely with Bread of Lupinum which is well baked and knea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with Salt and leaven, and who has drunk nothing but red Wine, adding thereto as much Honey.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="63" type="part">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:59943:38"/>
               <head>63. <hi>Againſt Hoarſneſs.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Foraſmuch as the Speech is of a great moment, the want and neceſſity of which cauſes us to ſeek for means which may take away all hindrances, and aſſiſt the ſame: amongſt one of the moſt trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome is Hoarſneſs, which makes men ſpeak ſoftly, and with great difficulty. This will be cured by the following means, by which the Voice ſhall become clearer and more perceptible.</p>
               <p>The Patient ſhall take at night going to bed, two ounces, or [four or five thin ſmall ſpoonsful] of Wine, in which good Figs and Raiſons have been boyl'd for two hours together, with Sugar, Cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon, and Cloves.</p>
               <p>Alſo water wherein red Coleworts have been boyl'd, adding thereto one ounce of Syrup of Venus-hair; and that he ſhall take in the morning.</p>
               <p>The Voice is alſo made clear by little Cakes made of Diairis-powder, and taken in the morning and at night.</p>
               <p>Alſo Syrup of Jujuben, as alſo the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction of Elicampane made with Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar and with Honey, in which Liquoris has been boyl'd, performs the ſame.</p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:59943:38"/>
               <p> An excellent Remedy againſt this evil, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s to take this at night when you go <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o bed; for it makes the almoſt-loſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>peech to be reſtored again.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Brandy-Syrup.</head>
                  <p>Put one ounce of fine Sugar that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oudered in a little flat diſh; pour there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon of the beſt Brandy as much as is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eceſſary for to cover the Sugar ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ntly; put the diſh upon a Coal-fire, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t the Brandy afire with a burning-paper, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>newing the ſame as often as the flame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oes out: Stir the Sugar without ceaſing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ll it ceaſe burning. All the remaining <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>quor which ſhall be left on the bottom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f the little porenger, not being above <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne ſpoonful and a half, the Patient ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ake while it is hot. Then you ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>me his Night-cap with Frankincenſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>arniſh or Gum of Juniper-tree, Maſtick, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orax, Benzoin; nay, you ſhall take Tow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Flax which perfume, and lay it upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he head.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Dyet.</head>
                  <p>But whatſoever is the cauſe of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oarſneſs, it is neceſſary to abſtain from
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:59943:39"/> ſowre and ſalt Victuals, from raw Fruits Fiſh, and ſlimy things; alſo from Beans Peaſe, Cheſnuts, and other windy things as well as from heavy bread; from drin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king Wine between Meals, from ſleeping in day-time, from going in the cold, wind or in the Sun: but above all, from ſtrain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing his Voice by loud ſpeaking, or ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> going; ſilence and quiet being one par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the Cure.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="64" type="part">
               <head>64. <hi>Of Shortneſs of Breath.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Againſt ſhortneſs of the breath, or di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficulty in breathing (otherwiſe call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſhort-winded) beſides the means whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> are good againſt the Cough, this followin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Liquor is good, and very uſeful, bei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> made of theſe following, like unto a Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerve.</p>
               <p>Take large Raiſons without ſtones o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ounce, two great Figs, one Date, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Hyſop, Venus-hair, Liquoris well waſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Fox-lungs, diſtilled water of Scabioſa, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> each the eighth part of an ounce; Pen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dice two ounces, Syrup of Liquoris, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> each enough to the third parts of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Conſerve: of which Syrup, you ſhall u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with a little ſtick of Liquoriſh, a wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> after Dinner, before or after that you ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:59943:39"/> uſed a Decoction of the following. Take Venus hair, Marubium, of each one handful, Ani-ſeed, Licoriſh, Dates, Dry-figs, Seed of Fenickle, Ladies-mark, boiled in a pint of water, ſo long, till one third part is conſumed; uſe this every morning two hours before breakfaſt; and preſently after it, or a little before it, eat a little cake of Diairis, or Diahyſopum; anoint the Breaſt with a Salve which is made of this follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>Take Oyl of Sweet Almonds two oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, freſh May-Butter one ounce, a little Saffron, New wax, (as much as is enough) melted and mingled to a chafing Salve.</p>
               <p>For as much as the ſhort-windedneſs is worſe than the Hoarſeneſs or Cough, you muſt take greater care in your Diet when troubled with the ſhort-windedneſs, than if you have a Cough. Therefore you muſt abſtain from the aforeſaid, and all other windy Meats; and contrariwiſe you ſhall feed upon peeled Barley, boiled in ſweet Almonds-milk with Sugar, the juice of red Cabbage; or, you ſhall eat of old Cock with Hyſop and Saffron; you ſhall eat Hens, Pigeons, and the like, roaſted Figs, Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Dates, ſugared kernels, Pine-Apples, Almonds: moderate motion is good, but above all, it is very bad to beſtir himſelf
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:59943:40"/> much before dinner; and the pertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation and diſtraction of the mind is far worſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="65" type="part">
               <head>65. <hi>A Remedy for a Cough.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take Hyſop, Colts foot, of each one handful; Figs, large Raiſons, Liquoriſh, of each one ounce; boil this in water, till two third parts are waſted, and drink thereof twice a day, two hours before din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and one hour before ſupper.</p>
               <p>Or, let the Patient drink twice a day of Red cole-worts, with a handful of Colts-foot, and one or two ſmall ſtalks of Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſop; and theſe things muſt boil a little time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="66" type="part">
               <head>66. <hi>Againſt the pain in the ſide.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Againſt the pain in the ſide, <hi>(Pleuriſis<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>)</hi> drink immediately Syrop of Violets, or others that are proper for the Breaſt, with two half ounces of Nettle-ſeed or Aſhen-tree-ſeed, or water of <hi>Carduus Benedictus,</hi> our Ladies-Thiſtle, or of Bryer, or in a ſpoonful of white-wine, the powder of haſel-nut-ſhells, the eighth part of an ounce, eighteen grains of Red-Coral; theſe things being well mingled together,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:59943:40"/> add thereto the Seed of Melions, Gourds and Cowcombers, (being very uſeful for this purpoſe) this you ſhall take luke-warm, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſoon as it is poſſible after you perceive the Diſtemper. Or, roaſt in the hot aſhes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſweet Apple: when it is roaſted enough, then mingle it with the juice of Lickoriſh, Starch, and white Sugar; give the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ient this twice a day, two hours before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inner or ſupper: or, take the eighth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>art of an ounce of the powder of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oars Tooth, with juice of ſweet-Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds and Sugar-candy: or, with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uice of Red-coleworts, barley-water, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e like things that are ſpecifical for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reaſt: or make aſhes of the piſle of an Ox, and give the Patient thereof to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rink, the eighth part of an ounce, with white-wine, or with Carduus Benedictus, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r Barley-water; if this be uſed before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e third day, it is a ſpecial Remedy.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>How to make Aſhes of the Piſle of an Ox.</head>
                  <p>Their Aſhes are made in this manner; They cut the Piſle in pieces, laying it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n an even hearth, covered with a new <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ot, and round about the ſame fiery burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>g coals, or hot aſhes, renewing the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> many times, till it is turned into aſhes;
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:59943:41"/> for which, almoſt a whole day is required<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but if this pain continues, let him uſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Decoction of Roſes, Poppies, or on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> eighth part of an ounce of the powde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thereof, with the water of Scabioſa, and Pimpernel, and Syrrup of Hyſop; other<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wiſe with Syrrup of Violets: but if ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is not any hope to be cured by this, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> take one of the beſt ſweet Apples, tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> out the kernels, and fill it again wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fine white Frankincenſe; wrap it up <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Tow or Flax, and let it roaſt ſlowl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in the aſhes, and give him this to ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> who is troubled with the pain in the ſid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="67" type="part">
               <head>67. <hi>Againſt vomiting of Blood.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Againſt the Vomiting of Blood, dri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſtilled water of the firſt budding or puttin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> out of Oak-leaves, or the Decoction Wall-wort, Lambs-tongue, Thouſand-bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ton, or of Horſe-tail; or let him ſwallo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> down a little piece of Maſtick, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Harts-horn, Goats-horn, Bolus Armeni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Terra ſigillata, red Corals or Amber; the powder of the innermoſt little ſhels Cheſtnuts, or Cork, or Hogs-dung roa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> with unſalted Butter; this you ſhall gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> him to eat.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="68" type="part">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:59943:41"/>
               <head>68. <hi>A Cure for the Conſumption.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>For the comfort and eaſe of thoſe who are in a Conſumption, theſe means are uſeful: The Patient ſhall drink eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry morning four hours before meat, a little draught of Milk of a ſhe-Aſs, or of a Bitch freſh milk'd, putting eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry time therein one ounce of pounded <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oaf-Sugar; he ſhall take every hour Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve of Roſes, or loaf-Sugar, or of the powder of ſmall Cakes, called Diatraga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canth: it is very good to drink every morning faſting a full glaſs of water, which is ſtill'd in a bath <hi>(balneum Mariae,)</hi> made of all theſe Herbs, <hi>viz.</hi> of Colts-foot, Wall-wort, Venus-hair, Hyſop, of each a like quantity, with ſnails without the ſhells, being waſht very clean: the water of Snails ſtilled alone, is good alſo againſt this diſtemper, as well as for all other dry and lean perſons: he ſhall uſe little Cakes made of two ounces of Pimpinella, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered with Sugar, which he ſhall take eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry morning, being diſſolved in three ounces of Pimpernella water: it is very wholeſome to take in the morning of this following powder, a quarter of an ounce, and immediately after take two ſpoonfuls
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:59943:42"/> of Surrup of Jujuben, or for want of that<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> take ſtilled water of Colts-foot, or of Barley-water <hi>(Ptiſane.)</hi> This Powder is made in this manner.</p>
               <p>Take of the four great cooling ſeeds together, one ounce and three quarters, Quince-kernels almoſt half an ounce, white Poppy ſeed ſomewhat more then half a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ounce, Liquoriſh balls, pounded Hyſop, Starch, Gum-Arabick, three ſixteen parts of an ounce, Gum-Diatragacanth, Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, as much as of all the reſt together; this being each aſunder well pounded, and reduced to Powder, muſt be well mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> together to a Powder.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="69" type="part">
               <head>69. <hi>To cure the Palpitation of the Heart.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The Patient by the advice of the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician, muſt either bleed or purge, that if it be poſſible the cauſe of the Malady may be taken away.</p>
               <p>The outward Remedies againſt his ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, (when 'tis accompanied with an Ague) will be to drink every morning the Surrup of Lemmons, or the juyce of Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel with Roſe-water, Purſlain with Sorrel.</p>
               <p>Let the Patient ſmell to Spices that ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of a good ſcent and cooling; as Roſes, Flowers of Violets, and Vineger.</p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:59943:42"/>
               <p> Alſo wet a cloth in ſtilled water of Lambs-tongue, Roſes, and Sorril, with a little wine-vineger, and put it upon the left breaſt.</p>
               <p>But if the paſſion of the Heart be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an Ague, then take Imperial water, <hi>(Aqua Coeleſtis)</hi> Cinnamon-water, Aqua Vitae or Brandy; drink of each of theſe apart in the morning faſting: or, diſtilled water of Ox-tongue, in which three oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Cloves have been boiled, or ſix ounces of the water of Confilie, the Herb Balm, with two ounces of Sugar mixed therewith: or, the weight of a Crown of the Conſerve of Diameſchum. Let him drink with it diſtilled water of good wine, or water of Ox-tongue, or the Confection of Hyacinth, (which is very good) or the Conſerve of Gilliflowers, and Roſemary, or ſuch like.</p>
               <p>Alſo take the water of Ox-tongue, Balm, and Bourage, (a pound together) good red-Wine half a pint, ſugar of Cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon, Cloves, Nutmegs, of each a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an ounce; mingle all theſe together, warm it in a diſh upon an hot Tile, then wet therein a Scarlet or linnen cloth, and put it upon the left breaſt.</p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:59943:43"/>
               <p> You ſhall put in a little bag the Powder of Sandalwood with the aforeſaid well-ſcent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Spices, and heart-ſtrengthening Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and lay it warm upon the left breaſt.</p>
               <p>The aforeſaid pleaſant ſcents comfort the Heart, therefore the Patient ſhould of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſmell to them, whether you prepare them for Perfumes, Waters, Powders, or ſweet-balls made of Benjamin, Storax, Labdanum, Ambergreeſe, Civet, or other rich Perfumes, wherewith you may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ume the ſick parties Chamber &amp; Cloaths.</p>
               <p>Alſo theſe Perfumes are good to hang about the ſick parties neck, about the big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a pea: or, to drink two or three ounces of the diſtilled water of Ox-tongue, and of Balme.</p>
               <p>Alſo this following water is eſteemed a ſpecial Remedy: Take of the Hearts of three Oxen, and the Hearts of three Hogs, Nutmegs, Cloves, Seed of Baſilicon, of each three eight parts of an ounce; flowers of Burage, Ox-tongue, Roſemary, Mary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>golds, of each an handful; let theſe ſoak one night in Old Malligo or Hipocras.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="70" type="part">
               <head>70. <hi>To cure the faintneſs of the Heart.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>'Tis good to preſs and bend the joint of the Heart or Phyſick-finger, or to rub
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:59943:43"/> the ſame with a piece of Gold and Saffron: for from this finger, the vertue goes to the Heart.</p>
               <p>But foraſmuch as this is a very bad and heavy diſtemper, and a fore-runner of death, therefore 'tis called a timely death. For which a ſpeedy Remedy muſt be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, and be always in readineſs: if it be but cold water, which they muſt ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle on the Patients face, adding thereto Roſe-water, if it may be gotten time enough.</p>
               <p>Their fingers, arms, and legs muſt be tyed, and rubbed hard: they muſt pull the ſick by the hair, and give him a little wine to drink.</p>
               <p>Or, give him ſome Aqua-vitae, or Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theglin, made a little warm, or Imperial water, <hi>(Aqua Coeleſtis)</hi> or let him ſmell good wine-vineger, or rub and anoint his Breaſt with Aqua vitae, (made a little warm,) by which Motions and Drink the diſperſed vitals will gather themſelves again to the heart.</p>
               <p>Theſe means are good for men, but not for women, although you are aſſured the faintneſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> proceeds not from the Matrix; if it doth, ſprinkle not any water on her face, but let her ſmell fumes that ſtink, putting them into her Noſtrils.</p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:59943:44"/>
               <p> Such as, Divel-turd, Beverſwine, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridge Feathers burnt on the fire, old ſhoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoals burned: or you ſhall perfume her below with Benzoyn, Storax, Musk, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, Civet, and the like.</p>
               <p>If the faintneſs proceeds from the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of the ſpirit, as it often doth, after a great bleeding, looſeneſs or ſweat, then it is not good to bind the arms and legs, nor to ſprinkle cold water on their face, but 'tis moſt expedient to give them good wine, and of the aforeſaid waters to drink, and to nouriſh them with good Victuals, as Chicken-broth, and the like nouriſhing, ſoft, and delicate food.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="71" type="part">
               <head>71. <hi>Againſt continual Burning Feavers.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Bind upon the Pulſe-veins of both Arms the juyce of ſtinging Nettles, mingled with Poplar Salve: or take an Oni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the middle being taken out, then fill it with Mithridate, and bind it faſt upon the pulſe of the Right-arm.</p>
               <p>Or, two yolks of new-laid Eggs, with foot of the chimney well pounded, ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with Salt and ſtrong vineger; bind it with a linnen cloth about the arm.</p>
               <p>Or, take the heart of a frog, and bind it on the Heart or Back-bone of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:59943:44"/> or lay it on his Liver, or lay upon the hollow of the foot a living frog.</p>
               <p>Many make a drink of bruiſed field-Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, to drink in the greateſt heat, and make of the remainder a Poultis to lay upon the back of the Patients hands.</p>
               <p>Others perform the ſame with the juyce of a great Lemon: others lay flea-herb-ſeed, or five-leav'd graſs a ſoaking in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter one night, and then putting Sugar in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this liquor, they give it the Patient to drink.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="72" type="part">
               <head>72. <hi>Againſt Quotidian Feavers.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>It is good to drink (a little before the fit cometh) the juyce of Betony and Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine leaves; or to drink in the morning a Decoction of the Roots of Ladies-mark, Parſley, Radiſh, and Aſparagus, the leaves of Betony and Harts-tongue, red Spaniſh Peaſe, and the middle bark of an Alder-tree.</p>
               <p>Or, drink every morning and night, two leaves of five-fingers Herb, with a draught of white-wine: or the Roots of Poppies, and drink a draught thereof about an hour before the fit comes; and in the mean time forbear ſleeping. Alſo bind upon the pulſe of the Arms, a Pultiſe
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:59943:45"/> made of noble Say, Hyſop, Wormwood, Parſley, Mint, and three-leaved-graſs with white ſpots; pound theſe with wine-vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neger to a Poultis, and make thereof ſmall plaiſters for the pulſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="73" type="part">
               <head>73. <hi>A Remedy for the Tertian Feaver.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Soak pounded Patience Roots, three or four hours in white-wine; ſtrain the juyce through a fine cloth, (that it may make about ſixteen ounces) and let the patient drink it an hour or two before his Feaver cometh: or put the ſame a ſoaking in half wine and water, with Platine Root.</p>
               <p>Or, take about half a pint of Lambs-tongue, Purſlain, or Pimpernel-water, a little before the fit come: or, drink every day in the morning and at night, three leaves of five-finger Herb in wine.</p>
               <p>Or, take the juyce of Ladies Mark, Sage, wine-vineger, of each an ounce; mingle theſe together to a potion, take it three hours before the Feaver come.</p>
               <p>But the beſt Remedy in the world, is to drink two ounces of the juyce of Pome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>granats in the morning faſting, five hour before the fit come, and to bind upon t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> wreſts ſleep-browns, and in the hollow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the feet piles as big as a pea, made of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:59943:45"/> ounce of Poplar-ſeed, and one half ounce of Spiders-web put thereon, until the fit be paſt: Or, you may (an hour before the fit come) lay this poultis upon the pulſes: Sage, Nettle, Rhue, of each an handful, plucked before the Sun riſe; Salt, Soot, of each as big as a Nut; pound theſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with wine-vineger to a poultis.</p>
               <p>Others do more commend a Salve made of Earth-worms boyled in Gooſe-greaſe; anoint the fore-head therewith, and the patients Temples, before his fit cometh: or, put to his Neck the horns of a flying Hart, <hi>(Horbeder)</hi> this is a ſingular Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="74" type="part">
               <head>74. <hi>How to Cure a Quartan Feaver.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take two white loaves, as hot as they come out of the Oven, let them ſoak in a pot of wine-vineger; ſtill it through a Still, and give the patient of this ſtilled wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to drink about half a pint, two hours before his Feaver come: or, the juyce of the female wool-herb is a ſpec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, being preſt out with white-wine, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it buds, and taken a little before the fit comes.</p>
               <p>The juyce of the Herb Colts-foot hath the ſame vertue: alſo the Decoction of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:59943:46"/> the Roots and leaves of Iron-herb, boyled in white-wine.</p>
               <p>Alſo the Decoction of clean-Mint, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, Oreya, Oxentongue, Borage, Betony, Thime, Agrimony, the rind of Thama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risk Root, Aſh, and Sparagus Roots boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led up together in white-wine: or the powder of Myrrha drunk with Maligoe; likewiſe pills of Myrrha and Triacle, of the bigneſs of a Spaniſh pea, ſwallowed down an hour before the fit come.</p>
               <p>Alſo diſtilled water, or the Decoction of Carduus Benedictus, drunk before the fit come, is very good.</p>
               <p>Alſo the juyce of Wormwood and Rhue ſetled and clear: or the juyce of Lambs-tongue drunk with honey-water. Alſo the pounded Root of Mans-ear, dryed in the Sun, or in an Oven, the eighth part of an ounce, taken half a quarter of an hour before the fit come.</p>
               <p>Alſo if you drink one ounce or two of the juyce of bruiſed Alder-roots, once, twice, or thrice before the fit come, it will leave you: or having purged, drink white-wine wherein Sage hath been ſteeped a whole night; beſides, anoint the back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone, the hollow of the feet, the palms of the hands, the fore-head and the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, with Treacle, Mithridate, or Scorpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on-Oyl:
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:59943:46"/> the Oyl of Bay-berries, mingled with Brandy, hath the ſame vertue.</p>
               <p>Some ſuperſtitiouſly eat Sage for nine days together, the firſt day nine leaves, the ſecond eight, and ſo conſequently eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day one leſs, until the nine days be paſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="75" type="part">
               <head>75. <hi>A Cure for the Shaking in the Ague.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Eat before the fit come, a peeled head of Garlick.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="76" type="part">
               <head>76. <hi>Againſt Thirſt in an Ague.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Hold upon your Tongue a three come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſtone, which is found in the head of a Carp, a ſtone of a Snail, a piece of Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtal often laid in water, a piece of Silver or Gold, or leaves of Roman Sorril, of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlain, of Stan-crop, or peeled ſeed of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbers, Houſe-leek leaves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="77" type="part">
               <head>77. <hi>A Remedy againſt the Plague.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Make diſtilled water of the Queen of the fields, ſteeped before in White-Wine: or put a piece of Gold, or, of its filings, or leaves of beaten Gold, a ſoaking in the juyce of Lemons twenty four hours; min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle this with Wine-vineger, and with the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:59943:47"/> powder and decoction of Angelica-roots, and give it to him that hath the Plague: or take two old Oaker-nuts, one Fig, ten leaves of Rhue, one corn of Salt, bruiſe theſe together, then mingle them, and roaſt them in the aſhes, and ſprinkle them with Wine to an Antidote, and give it to the infected perſon.</p>
               <p>Or, take an head of Garlick, leaves of Rhue, the Herb Salandine, of each twenty; pound them together with White-wine, and a little Brandy that is let through, to a potion; of this let him drink half a pint.</p>
               <p>Three quarters of a pint of Wine, ſix ounces of the Water of Orange-flowers, drunk, driveth away the Malignity of the diſtemper by ſweating: ſo doth the juyce of Marygolds, Gilliflowers, and of the Herb Scabioſa.</p>
               <p>Upon the ſwelling of the Plague, you muſt lay a hot loaf being opened in the middle: or a white Onion filled with Treacle or Mithridate, made ſoft with the juice of Lemon, well ſtopped and roaſted in the aſhes till it is enough; then bruiſe it, and lay it upon the ſwelling.</p>
               <p>Alſo they may drink the juyce that is preſſed thereout, and lay the remainder upon the ſwelling; which hath the ſame vertue.</p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:59943:47"/>
               <p> Againſt the Carbunckle, or other peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lential ſwellings, take pounded Rhue, with ſowr Leaven, Figs, Spaniſh flyes, Onion, Sea-Onion, unquenched Lime, Soap, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniack, and a little Venice-Treacle; make a plaiſter thereof, lay it to the ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and it will break them.</p>
               <p>Or, dry a Toad, either in the Sun or in the Oven; make her into powder, lay the powder on the ſwelling, it will draw out the poiſon.</p>
               <p>Or, put thereupon a living Frog; if he dyes, lay on an other, and renew this of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, till the Frog remains alive, ſo you ſhall draw out all the poiſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="78" type="part">
               <head>78. <hi>A Cure for Hanging-Breaſts.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Make a Salve of the remainder of the dregs of Flax-ſeed Oyl, a little gum of Arabia, Dragant, Maſtick, and Campher, or Partridge Eggs; renew it often.</p>
               <p>Or, waſh them with the diſtilled water of freſh Pine-Apples, or with the juyce of wild Pine-Apples.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="79" type="part">
               <head>79. <hi>A Cure for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcerated Breaſts.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>If the Breaſt be ulcerated becauſe of the ſuperfluity of ſuck, take mire out of the Grinders or Cutlers trough, and cover the Breaſt therewith, and the pain will Goard-ceaſe
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:59943:48"/> in one night; you may add there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto a little Oyl of Roſes.</p>
               <p>But if the Teats be much infected, lay thereupon the pap of Rice-Meal, or the flour of the beſt Wheat, boyled thick in Red-wine, as hot as you can ſuffer it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="80" type="part">
               <head>80. <hi>How to increaſe Milk.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Uſe often Fenickle-juyce, or drink the juyce of Ladies-mark, or of Beets; or powder of the Root of our Lady-Thiſtle, adding thereto freſh Fenickle-ſeed, and a little burnt powder of the fore-feet of a Cow, with Wine, or Chicken-broth, or ſuch like: or, fine powder of Mountain Chryſtal, drunk with Wine or Mutton-broth; or, eat boyl'd Coleworts, prepared with Pepper; or, boyled Roots of Neck-herb with Pepper.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="81" type="part">
               <head>81. <hi>How to dry up Milk.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Lay upon the Teats the Roots of the Herb Salandine, bruiſed and boiled: or, bath the Breaſts with ſowre vineger wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or lay thereupon a pap of Bean-Meal; or of Rhue, Sage, Mint, Wormwood, Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nickle, and rolls ſodden and mingled with Cameles Oyl, or freſh and green Goard-leaves, or bruiſed and pounded Crab-fiſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="82" type="part">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:59943:48"/>
               <head>82. <hi>Againſt any hurt by ſwallowing down Horſe-leeches.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>If any in drinking have ſwallowed down any Horſe-leech, or ſuch like, give him to drink wood-lice, with ſtrong vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
               <p>If a Serpent be crept into the body of any being aſleep, having his mouth open, nothing is better than to receive through a funnel in the mouth, the ſmoak of an old ſhoo-ſole: or drink a Decoction of Iron-hearb boiled in white-wine, <hi>probatum eſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If you have eaten bad Muſhromes, then drink Honey-Vineger, with pounded hens-dung, and you ſhall preſently be freed from any harm, or ſuffocation of the ſtomack; or drink lie of Vine-branches with a little Salt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="83" type="part">
               <head>83. <hi>Againſt the Hiocough.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>It is good to ſtop and retain oftentimes the breath, to ſtop both Ears, keeping up the head, and the mouth open, looking upwards.</p>
               <p>Alſo endeavour to ſneeze, to uſe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, to ſuffer thirſt, to throw cold wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter on the patients face, and to make him afraid.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="84" type="part">
               <head>84. <hi>Againſt Belching.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>It is good to eat faſting, pounded Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nickle,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:59943:49"/> Anis, Carawaies, and Coriander: or to drink twice or thrice in the morning the Decoction of Bay-berries boyled in wine, with the afore-ſaid ſeeds, and to lay upon the ſtomach a little bag of worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, Rhue, Marjoram, and water-Mint.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="85" type="part">
               <head>85. <hi>To ſtrengthen the Stomach.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>If the weakneſs of the ſtomach proceed from an hot cauſe, then (if the patient perceive after eating and drinking a pain in the head, and ſtinking belching, with vomiting, accompanied with exceſſive ſlabber, and an inclination to vomit,) it will be convenient a loaf<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and an half, or an ounce and a quarter of Hiera-ſimplex, with the Decoction of Spaniſh peaſe, or two or three ounces of water of Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, and after Meals, to uſe prepared Coriander, abſtaining to drink ſuddenly after it, or to ſleep in the day time.</p>
               <p>Alſo 'twill be good to take once a week, a Confection of Myrobalan, to ſtrengthen the ſtomach; but if the patients mouth be dry, thirſty, and brackiſh, let him take Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rup of Roſes, Sorrel, and of Quince, with Cicory, or Endive-water, or boyled water made cold again; then let him take Bitter-holly as above.</p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:59943:49"/>
               <p> You ſhall anoint the ſtomach with Oyl of Roſes and Quinces, and lay thereupon a Plaiſter of red-Roſes, Sandal-wood, and other cooling and heart-ſtrengthening things; but none that are heating, leſt you increaſe the evil.</p>
               <p>If the weakneſs of ſtomach proceed from tough ſlime in the top of the ſtomach, which cauſeth a ſowre wind, and hindreth concoction; take Pills proper for the ſame, by your Phyſicians advice.</p>
               <p>In this caſe Anis and Fenickle is good after meals, and toaſted bread ſoaked in boyled Wine, Hypocras, or Malmſey.</p>
               <p>For outward Remedy, 'tis good to anoint the ſtomach with Oyl of Maſtick, and of Nardus, and ſometimes to lay upon it the ſame toaſted Bread, ſoaked in good Wine, covered with powder of Cloves and Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megs; or to wear on the ſtomach a Plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of theſe following things, Maſtick, Labdanum, of each an ounce, powdered or pounded Wormwood, and Mint, of each one eighth part of an ounce, Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine as much as is needful to mingle the other to a Plaiſter; this being mix'd according to art, you ſhall ſpread it upon a piece of Leather.</p>
               <p>This weakneſs of the ſtomach proceeds manytimes from ſlime, which falleth down
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:59943:50"/> from the head, whereby the ſtomach be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cold, doth with difficulty digeſt what it receiveth.</p>
               <p>The beſt Remedy is faſting, whereby the ſtomach is emptied at leiſure, digeſting the meat ſlowly. But when the pain is very great, then vomit to empty the ſtomach from that which troubleth it; or drink ſpiced Wine or Hypocras.</p>
               <p>Then ſtrengthen the ſtomach by heat and good ſents, as with Heart-ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Powders and Flowers, put into little bags, and lay them upon the ſtomach; they may be made of Cammomile, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joram, Rhue, Wormwood, Cloves, Cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon, and Nutmegs.</p>
               <p>And for the clearing of the ſtomach, let the Patient a little before meals take a little pill, or powder of bitter holly <hi>(Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra ſimplex)</hi> or if the ſtomach be much out of order, then let him take in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing three or four hours before dinner, three of the aforeſaid little Pills.</p>
               <p>Let the patient eat little, and light meats, and ſuch as will eaſily digeſt; as boyled meat, and fleſh eaſie of digeſtion.</p>
               <p>Let him drink good wine, yet little, ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome water, but never ſowre wine, or new wine. After Meals let him take a ſpoonful of this following Powder, (which
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:59943:50"/> the ſtomach will digeſt,) Take Aniſeed, Lemon-ſeed, Cinnamon, Liquoriſh, ſcra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings of Ivory, one ſixteenth part of an ounce, loaf-Sugar as much as is neceſſary; mingle this to a fine powder.</p>
               <p>Let the patient be well cloathed againſt the cold; let him keep his head and feet moderately warm, and always dry; let him keep to his ſtomach a piece of Crimſon cloth, upon which let him ſpread Gilli-flowers, Cinnamon, and other well-ſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed powders; or a Kites skin, or other ſoft skin to keep his ſtomach warm.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="86" type="part">
               <head>86. <hi>Againſt the Loathing of the ſtomach.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>From the great abundance of Slime, of courſe and tough humours, the ſtomach is brought to loath that which it receives, and agreeth not with the patients taſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing continually hindred by reaſon of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual dryneſs and bitterneſs in the mouth, ſometimes vomiting yellow ſtuff as bitter as gall: for a Remedy, the Gall is to be cleanſed, the patient is to bleed, and uſe ſuch means as may conduce to his recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: to make him hungry, let him drink in the morning a Decoction of Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, or juyce of Mint; and for the ſharpning of the Appetite, and comforting
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:59943:51"/> the ſtomach, let him take fig-beans made in ſweet-water, then pound them with wine-vineger, and ſo drink them.</p>
               <p>The ſame effect hath the Gum of the Cherry-tree taken with wine and water.</p>
               <p>Alſo a Decoction of wild Chervel, or courſe Marjoram, as well as Indian Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and the kernels of the fruits of Sance-tree, <hi>(Berberries.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo the ſeed of young Rapes with ſuger, or the ſame ſeed laid in pickle and Oyl: but in caſe none of theſe means will help, then give the patient all ſorts of Meats, according to his will and diſcretion, (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they be not good for him.) He ſhall alſo ſatisfie his deſire in his ordinary drink, and uſe clean juyce of Pomegra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nats alone, or mixed with wine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="87" type="part">
               <head>87. <hi>Againſt Vomiting.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take a ſlice of Toſted-bread, let it ſteep in Clarret-wine, and ſpread there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon powder of Maſtick, and lay it warm upon the ſtomach, renewing it every three hours.</p>
               <p>Or, take water-Mint two handfuls, red-Roſes one handful; let them boyl up in wine: then take Toaſted-bread, well ſoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in wine, two ounces; mix theſe with
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:59943:51"/> powder of Maſtick, one eighth part of an ounce to a Poltis, to prepare the ſtomach againſt the Symptome.</p>
               <p>But if the Vomiting be accompanyed with a Feaver, then ſoak and boil the Mint, Roſes, and Toaſted-bread, in vineger.</p>
               <p>Alſo Mint, or water-Mint bruiſed, ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with Oyl of Roſes, and laid upon the ſtomach, is good againſt all kinds of Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting; beſides, it is good after Meals to ſwallow a mouthful of water: or to eat a piece of Quince-Herb, without drinking ſuddenly after it: or to ſwallow in the moming with Wine, two hours before break-faſt, five or ſix whole pepper-grains: or Syrup of Mint or Wormwood, or green Ginger.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe it is expedient to bleed by Cupping-Glaſſes, on the lowermoſt part of the ſtomach, or under the Navel, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out pricking, eſpecially when you eat; and to reſt after Meal without ſpeaking or coughing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="88" type="part">
               <head>88. <hi>A Cure for the pain of the Stomach.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Fill a diſh with hot aſhes, ſprinkle them with Wine, cover the diſh all over with a cloth; hold this warm to your belly:
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:59943:52"/> or lay warm upon the ſtomach a little bag of Salt very warm.</p>
               <p>Or, take crums of Bread, as hot as they come out of the oven, put it in the Oyl of Cammomile; after it hath ſoaked therein, wrap it up in a linnen cloth, and lay it upon the belly.</p>
               <p>Or, fill the bladder of a Hog with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction of Laurel, Oreya, Marjoram, Mint, Thime, Cammomile, Nipta, Melilot, Anis, and Fenickle; lay it warm upon the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, and renew it when it begins to be cold.</p>
               <p>Or, knead a cake of Rye-leaven with Wine, and an handful of Wormwood, water-Mint, and Roſes, and lay it to the belly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="89" type="part">
               <head>89. <hi>To kill the Worms in Children.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Let them eat confection of Rhabarbar, or the Preſerve of Peach-tree flowers.</p>
               <p>Or, drink diſtilled water of Gentian.</p>
               <p>Or, the juyce of Lemons, water-Mint, Baſilicon, Purſlain, Rhue, or Wormwood.</p>
               <p>Or, a ſmall draught of Wormwood-Wine, with the Powder of Earth-worms, firſt dryed, and then burnt upon an hot Tile, and afterwards pounded ſmall.</p>
               <p>Or, the eighth part of an ounce o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:59943:52"/> the Powder of Carduus Benedictus, or Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallina.</p>
               <p>Or, lay upon their Navel a Poltis of Wormwood, and an Ox-gall, in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the Moon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="90" type="part">
               <head>90. <hi>A Cure for the Griping of the Guts.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>There is nothing better than to carry about one a Ring, or little box of Silver, in which is incloſed a ſmall piece of the Navel of a new-born Child; let the Ring touch the fleſh.</p>
               <p>Alſo, let the Patient (during the pain) drink a ſmall draught of the beſt white or red-wine.</p>
               <p>Or, drink four or five ounces of Oyl of Nuts, of Flax-ſeed, of Peach-tree kernels.</p>
               <p>Or, drink Cammomile-water, or water in which Hempſeed hath been boiled: or, Wine, in which ſtamp'd Elicampane-Root hath been ſoaked ten or twenty hours: or, the Powder of the pizzle of a Stag, drunk with water: or, Hens-dung, with Hypocraſs made of honey and wine.</p>
               <p>The little bones which are found in Woolfs-dung being bruiſed; nay, the dung of the Woolf bruiſed, and drank with Wines, is good againſt the Colick.</p>
               <p>Or, take the Heart of a Lark newly
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:59943:53"/> killed, and bind it to the calve of the leg.</p>
               <p>Alſo a Clyſter made of pickle.</p>
               <p>Alſo, a freſh skin, or the net of the guts of a Weather newly killed, and laid warm to the belly.</p>
               <p>Alſo a Plaiſter made of Wolfs-dung.</p>
               <p>Or, take hot aſhes, and put them in a diſh or pot, pouring thereupon a glaſs of good red-wine: cover it with a cloth four double, and lay it upon the belly, this will give preſent eaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="91" type="part">
               <head>91. <hi>Againſt Oppilation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Againſt Oppilation, and for the molli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of the belly, eat in the morning ſweet black Cherries, Peaches, Figs, or Mulberries; drink the firſt juyce of Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worts, Beets, the leaves of Peet-cheefe, or of Lettice without Salt.</p>
               <p>Or, lay upon the belly pap made of the Root of Hogs-bread, the Gall of a Bull mixed with honey: Colloquint-leaves: or, make a Stick-pill of Bacon, Mallow, or Beets.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="92" type="part">
               <head>92. <hi>A Remedy for the flux of the Belly.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The looſeneſs or flux of the belly is of
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:59943:53"/> two ſorts: firſt, the Dienteria, which is moſt dangerous: it is occaſioned, when that which is eaten is by reaſon of great Indigeſtion thrown out as it was taken in, without any ſtinking.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is the looſeneſs called Diar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhoea, when there is onely a ſingle flux and courſe of wateriſh and ſlimy humours.</p>
               <p>There is a third flux called the red-flux, or Diſſenteria, wherein blood is mixed with the Excrement, or when the ſick voids blood onely.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Looſeneſs Dienteria.</head>
                  <p>Concerning the firſt, (becauſe ſuch fluxes happen ſeldome, but by a ſtrange accident, or to thoſe who dye becauſe of extreme Age, and becauſe the ſame is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous) they who are not able to pay the Phyſician, may make uſe of the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Remedy.</p>
                  <p>Let the ſick take Surrup of Wormwood, with honey of Roſes: or, with the water of Betony, Fenickle, and Wormwood, four or five mornings, of each a ſpoonful.</p>
                  <p>The patient ſhall excite vomiting, (in caſe he be not inclined thereto) by ſome means, (which are uſeful thereto.)</p>
                  <p>Next, he ſhall ſtrengthen the ſtomach
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:59943:54"/> with with Oyl of Nard, Spicknard, Mint, and Wormwood.</p>
                  <p>Or, with a ſtomach-plaiſter of Galenus, ſpread upon leather, and laid to the belly.</p>
                  <p>Or, you may put to the ſtomach a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle bag filled with Wormwood, Mint, and dry Marjoram.</p>
                  <p>In the morning let him take a little piece of the ſmall Cakes which are made of Aromatick powder, (which you may have at the Apothecaries) called Aromaticum Roſatum.</p>
                  <p>Alſo a little of a well-ſugared Lemon-Pill; and before he eateth, let him take ſome Marmelade.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Second Looſeneſs, Diarrhoea.</head>
                  <p>For the ſecond, that this looſeneſs or flux of humours is not always a ſickneſs, but rather a benefit of nature, and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to him that hath it, if it be not accompanied with a Feaver, if it laſts not long, and if there be not any bloody flux to be feared.</p>
                  <p>When this looſeneſs is without a Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, you muſt let it take its courſe for three or four days, that the body may be exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated of bad and ſuperfluous humours.</p>
                  <p>At the end of that time, (if it be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:59943:54"/> with a Feaver,) or if you fear a bloody flux (being threatned by one drop of Blood) then you ſhall uſe theſe Clyſters or Infuſions which are drawing.</p>
                  <p>Take Mint, Sage, Marjoram, Benagie.</p>
                  <p>'Tis good to uſe Milk wherein Iron or Steel hath been quenched; or half Milk and half water boyled to the half.</p>
                  <p>Or, powder of Harts pizle drunk with water: or, roaſted Rice: or, the eighth part of an ounce of pownded Maſtick, with the yolk of an Egg.</p>
                  <p>Alſo you may make a Plaiſter of whea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Meal, ſoak'd in red-wine, and baked in an oven, and laid warm to the belly.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Bloody Flux.</head>
                  <p>Againſt the Bloody Flux, give the ſick red-Wine to drink, dried powder of Hare-blood, of powder of mans-bones, of a dogs-turd (the dog having fed three days upon Bones onely;) let theſe be dry, to make a powder of</p>
                  <p>This you ſhall give the ſick twice a day, for two or three days, with Milk where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in fiery flint-ſtones have been quenched.</p>
                  <p>Or, give him to drink ſtill'd water of Burſe, Prince-print: or, of the firſt ſprouts of Oaks: or, a Decoction of Bloudwort:
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:59943:55"/> or, powder of Lambs-tongue-ſeed: or, of burnt ſnails, and of bramble-berries, with a little pepper and gall-nuts: or, of burnt-Goats or Stags-horn: or, of the pizzle of an Hart, prepared as was ſhewed before, Sect. 66.</p>
                  <p>Drink alſo (to ſtop the flux) the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction of Dove-Nettles: uſe broth where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Coleworts have been well boiled: or, the juyce of Granates; nay, the Granate Apples themſelves, oftentimes Rhabarbar.</p>
                  <p>'Tis good alſo to uſe Sallats of Lambs-tongue and Sorrel.</p>
                  <p>Infuſions and Gliſters may be made of Lambs-tongue and Horſe-tail, and of all kind of ſtopping things. The Dyet may be found Sect. 114. of the Monthly Flux.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="93" type="part">
               <head>93. <hi>How to ſtop the exceſſive bleeding of the Vein under the Tongue.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Drink Lambs-tongue-water, with the eighth part of an ounce of Coral, hot Iron Scales pounded; warm them with a Decoction of Wool-leaves: or, inſtead thereof, a pap made up of burnt paper, the remainder of Lead: or, of Bolus Arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, with a little of the white of an Egg: or, powder of burnt or unburnt Oyſter-ſhells; mix theſe with a little freſh butter,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:59943:55"/> and lay it in a pap upon the Vein.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="94" type="part">
               <head>94. <hi>A Cure for the pain of the Paps.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Make a little pap of the crums of a white-loaf ſteeped in ſweet Milk; mingle it with two yolks of Eggs, a little Saffron, and Poplar Salve.</p>
               <p>Or, you may make an Oyntment of unſalted Butter, Flax-Seed-oyl, the yolk of an Egg, and a little wax.</p>
               <p>Or, you may make an Oyntment of freſh Butter, and burnt Cork; which is better than the perfume of grated Ivory.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="95" type="part">
               <head>95. <hi>Againſt a hot enflamed Liver.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Eat with your Meat Lettice, Sorril, Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlain, Cicory, and Hops; and drink ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſtilled water of the ſame Herbs: or, Endive-water: the water alſo in which theſe Herbs have been boyled is very good.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="96" type="part">
               <head>96. <hi>To Cure a ſtopped Liver.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Drink the Decoction of the Roots of Cicory, Parſley, Fenickle, Ladies-mark, Dogs-graſs, ſtinging Palm, Sorril, Venus-hair, Hops, and ſaw-duſt of Ivory.</p>
               <p>Alſo give the patient ſowr Surrup of
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:59943:56"/> Sea-Onion, <hi>(Oxymel Squilliticum.)</hi> Women ſometimes have Obſtructions in the Liver, when their Monthly flux is hindred: in ſuch caſe they ſhould bleed on the Mothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vein, <hi>(Saphena)</hi> being ſcituate about the Ankle, within the foot; and ſhe ſhould take at the new of the Moon, ſeven or eight mornings together, half an ounce of Triphera magna, and three ounces of the water of St. Johns Herb, Hyſop, of Fenickle, or its decoction; and of opening Roots boyled in water, and one third part of wine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="97" type="part">
               <head>97. <hi>A Remedy for the Jaundice.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Drink faſting one eighth part of an ounce of Goats-dung, after it hath ſtood nine days in white-wine.</p>
               <p>Or, a Decoction of Strawberry-leaves and Roots: or, take Mare-ſprigs, white-brambles or briars, about an handful, pluck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before Sun-riſing, Parſley-Roots two or three; pound them with white-Wine, (as much as will be neceſſary) ſtrain the wet through a cloth or ſive to a potion, and drink thereof morning and night the quantity of half a drinking-glaſs; this is an excellent Remedy, but not to be uſed by any woman with Child, but inſtead
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:59943:56"/> thereof bind on her Pulſes, and in the hollow of her feet, leaves of Mare-ſprigs, Oak, Salendine, and Malrove, bruiſed with a little wine to a pap.</p>
               <p>Or, Earth-worms waſhed in white-Wine, then dried and reduced to powder; take of this a ſmall ſpoonful, with ſome Wine.</p>
               <p>Or, the patient may drink the decocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Wormwood or Malrove: or, he may drink ſeveral days together, faſting, his own Urine: or, a little Wine with Goats-dung.</p>
               <p>Three leaves of wild-Rocket carried in the left hand, cureth (as ſome report) the Jaundice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="98" type="part">
               <head>98. <hi>To Cure the Black Jaundice.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The black Jaundice proceeds rather from the Milt, (or Spleen) than from the Liver.</p>
               <p>After the uſe of Syrrups, Potions and bleeding is good: or to ſet wind-cupping-glaſſes, without pricking, on the left ſide of the Milt.</p>
               <p>Then lay a piece of Felt thereon, being wet with good white-vineger made warm, and keep it to it while 'tis warm, warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng it three or four times.</p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:59943:57"/>
               <p> Then anoint the Milt (four or five days together) with a Salve of Dialthaea; and the following four or five days (or longer) wear thereon a Plaiſter made of Gum Ammoniack, melted in ſtrong vineger, and ſpread upon leather.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="99" type="part">
               <head>99. <hi>How to Cure the Dropſie.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Make a Potion of bruiſed Bryne-ſeed in white-wine: or, of the Flower of blew Flower-de-luce-wort: or, of Mans-Ear: or, drink for ſome days faſting your own water.</p>
               <p>Honey-water is a certain Remedy, with powder of Glaſs burnt ſeven times, and extinguiſhed again, mingled with the juyce of blew Flower-de-luce in white-wine.</p>
               <p>Lay upon the ſwoln place a Poltis of hot Cow-dung; with which, 'tis reported, a certain Phyſician of <hi>Myſia</hi> cured all Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies: or, lay on the Swelling live Snails, unwaſh'd, bruiſed with their ſhells.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="100" type="part">
               <head>100. <hi>A Cure for the Oppilation of the Milt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The Milt receiveth the black-gall, clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and purifying the Blood, that it may the better nouriſh. As long as it is in
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:59943:57"/> good order, it makes a man chearful and merry, but when it ſwells, and groweth bigger than is fit, by too much black gall, the Oppilation or ſtopping of the Milt is occaſioned, which hindreth good Blood; hereby nouriſhment is corrupted, the Members ſuffer and dry up, the Heart is ſad, the Face is black, and after meal the patient will find a pain in his left ſide.</p>
               <p>Whether it proceeds from an hot or cold humour, the Cure may be this.</p>
               <p>Open the Milt-Vein, <hi>(Salvatella)</hi> which is between the heart-finger and the little finger of the left hand.</p>
               <p>If the pain be accompanyed with thirſt, loathing, or dryneſs of the Tongue, 'tis a ſign the ſtopping proceeds from a hot humour.</p>
               <p>Then let the patient take four or five mornings faſting, Syrrup of Endive, or Harts-tongue.</p>
               <p>Then let him take a Potion of half an ounce of the juyce of Roſes, and three ounces of the Decoction of Harts-tongue and Caper-Roots, which the patient ſhall take five or ſix hours before dinner.</p>
               <p>Alſo half an ounce of Caſſia, and ſix eighth parts of an ounce of prepared Sene-powder, with water of Harts-tongue.</p>
               <p>Theſe cleanſing Potions being uſed,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:59943:58"/> anoint the Milt with oyl of Roſes, or Flax-ſeed: or, lay thereupon a Plaiſter of the aforeſaid Oyls with Flax-ſeed and Caper-Roots: or, of Night-ſhade, Purſlain-ſeed, and Powder of Lambs-tongue mingled with wine.</p>
               <p>If the ſick have but little deſire to eat, and cannot well digeſt what he hath eaten, or hath ſowr belchings, it ſheweth that his ſickneſs proceeds from black gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cold humours.</p>
               <p>Then given him a Syrrup of Staecha, and of Harts-tongue: or, vineger of honey ſetting of water, <hi>(Oxymel diureticum,)</hi> with a Decoction of Harts-tongue and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-Roots: you may (increaſing this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction) add thereto Roots of Ladies-mark, Parſley, Mint, and Thamarisk.</p>
               <p>Then purge the black gally humour with this Potion.</p>
               <p>Take Diacatholicum one ounce, prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Sene-powder a quarter of an ounce, water of Wormwood, or Harts-tongue, or of the aforeſaid Decoction three ounces, to a Potion.</p>
               <p>As for outward Remedies, you muſt anoint the ſide of the Milt with Oyl of Flower-de-luce, and of Dill, or with ſweet Butter, or Suet, Hens-greaſe, or Partridge Suet; mingle all theſe together.</p>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:59943:58"/>
               <p> Or, you may chafe the left ſide with the Salve of <hi>Dialthaea:</hi> let the ſick drink white-Wine, or the Decoction of Harts-horn, night and morning.</p>
               <p>Let him alſo eat two Figs, with the powder of Pepper, Hyſop, and Ginger; let him mingle his Wine with ſteeled wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: he ſhall alſo uſe Capers, with Oyl and Wine-vineger.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="101" type="part">
               <head>101. <hi>For the pain of the Milt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Againſt the pain and heavineſs of the Milt, drink Wine in which Hearts-tongue, Aſparagus, and Hops have been boiled.</p>
               <p>Or, drink often faſting, juyce of red-Coleworts which are half boyled.</p>
               <p>Or, the Decoction of Roman-Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, Hart-wort: or, of ſmall Santory or ſteeled-water.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="102" type="part">
               <head>102. <hi>Againſt the pain of the Graveliſh Colick.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Make a Decoction of the leaves and flowers of Camomile, boyled in half white-Wine and half water, until a third part <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e conſumed; give this to the patient to drink luke-warm, and the pain will ceaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="103" type="part">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:59943:59"/>
               <head>103. <hi>A Remedy for the Stone of the Reins.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>You ſhall often drink of Birchen ſprigs. This water muſt be gotten in the ſpring, becauſe the ſtock or rind being then cut, yields much water.</p>
               <p>Alſo the Fruit of Eglantine or ſweet-Brier before it be ripe, well ſugar'd, in the faſhion of a Marmelade: the ſeed which is incloſed in the Fruit being taken, (at the laſt quarter, and on the firſt days of the following New-Moon.)</p>
               <p>You ſhall often drink Wine with the powder of the Herb Reſt-harrow, or of Rhine-berries, or Gum which groweth on the rind of the Vine: or ſeed of Gooſe-graſs pounded ſmall: or, diſtilled water of Radiſh and Nettles, with ſome Sugar: or, water of Bryne-graſs: or, of wild <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> or, the juyce or water of Raddiſh, mingled with the Powder of burnt Egg-ſhells, Medlar-ſtones, Partridge-Eyes, Magpye-brains: or, the innermoſt skin of the ſtomach of a Hen or Capon: or, take the Roots of Eringo-Thiſtle, the Heart firſt taken out and made very clean; let it ſoak in Fountain-water eight hours; boil it to the conſumption of the half,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:59943:59"/> adding thereto bruiſed Liquariſh. Let it cool ſlowly; and uſe it in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faſting.</p>
               <p>For outward remedies, lay a Pultis upon the Reins, of Pellitory of the wall: or, of the Roots of Cypreſs, and leaves of the Roots of Alicampain boyled in Wine; but the beſt Remedy is, To prepare a Bath of water, in which are boyled the leaves of water-Parſley, Mallow, Poppies, Violets, Pellitory of the wall, &amp; Camomile-flowers; lay this on the Reins while you are in the Bath, a little bag with Rolls, and water-Parſley.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="104" type="part">
               <head>104. <hi>To take away the Stone of the Bladder.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Drink the juyce of Lemon with white-wine: or, bruiſe Medlar-ſtones, firſt waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Wine, and then dryed into a Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
               <p>Alſo the ſeed of Bryne, Pimpernels, Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paragus, Stone-break, Mellons, Pompeons, little Citrons, bruiſed in white-Wine.</p>
               <p>Or, make Powder of Spongy-ſtones, and of the ſtone which is found in the head of a Crab.</p>
               <p>Or, Haſel-nut-ſhells: or, Gum of black-Cherries, taken with White-wine, or the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:59943:60"/> juyce of Radiſhes: or, diſtilled water of the Husks of Beans, red Fitches, and the ſeed of Poppies.</p>
               <p>But beyond all, is, Glaſs made fiery hot, and quenched in water of Beans; or, Stone-break bruiſed ſmall, and given to the patient; it breaketh the ſtone in what place of the body ſoever.</p>
               <p>If it be in the Bladder, Egg-ſhells, out of which a little Chicken hath been ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and hatch'd, made into fine Powder, taken with white-Wine, water of Beans, ſtilled through the Helm, is excellent againſt the detention of the Urine, and ſtone of the bladder.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="105" type="part">
               <head>105. <hi>Againſt Scalding <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Uſe the Decoction of the four cold ſeeds: alſo, when you make water, hold your Privities in ſweet Milk.</p>
               <p>Or, take one eighth part of an ounce of the froth of the Sea made into Powder, and one ounce of the Marrow of Caſſia; then take the pap of Caſſia, with wine-vineger, and lay it upon the Reins, and other cooling things: never ſleep on your back.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="106" type="part">
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:59943:60"/>
               <head>106. <hi>To prevent Piſſing in Bed.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Eat often of a Goats-lung roaſted: or, drink Wine with the Powder of the Brains and ſmall Eloes of a Hare: or, of the blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of an Hog, Sheep, or Goat: or, the Powder of the Root of Liver-wort: or, Crow-foot, <hi>(Biſtorta)</hi> or, of Tormentil, with the juice of Lambs-tongue: or, Sheeps-Milk: or, the aſhes of the fleſh of an Hedg-hog.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="107" type="part">
               <head>107. <hi>Againſt Drop-Piſſing.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take whites of Eggs, Snails, of each one pound, of the four great cold ſeeds, ſmall ſeeds, of each half an ounce, Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice-water half a pound, Marrow of Caſſia four ounces, Turpentine three ounces; bruiſe what is to be bruiſed, ſet it ſoak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one night, and then ſtill it through an Helm, in a warm water-Bath, to a Potion.</p>
               <p>Let it ſtand before you uſe it: let the patient drink of this ſtilled water half an ounce, and one part of an ounce of Sugar of Roſes, continuing to do this ſome time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="108" type="part">
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:59943:61"/>
               <head>108. <hi>A Remedy againſt painful Piſſing.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Drink the juyce that is preſſed out of common Black-Cherries: or, out of win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Cherries, or the Decoction of the Roots of Radiſhes, Sorril, Eringo-Thiſtle, Elicampane-Root, white-brambles or bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Sparagus, Graſs, or of the Herb Reſt-harrow.</p>
               <p>Beſides, lay upon the yard, and round about the Privities, a pap made of fleas, mix'd with the Oyl of Bitter Almonds: or, with the fat of a Rabbet: or, which is better, put into the yard two or three fleas or Wood-lice: or, drink white-Wine, with bruiſed Cheeſlips, which are found in Cellars: or, make them into powder, and drink them with White-wine: or, the ſtilled water of the rinds of Reſt-har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row-wort, ſoaked before in Malmſey.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="109" type="part">
               <head>109. <hi>Againſt the Inflammation of the Yard.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take Cow-dung with flowers of Camo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mile, Brambles, and Melilot, to lay upon the Clods; this will take away the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flammation immediately; alſo the pap which ſhall be deſcribed, Sect. 110.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="110" type="part">
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:59943:61"/>
               <head>110. <hi>Againſt the Inflammation of the Matrix.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Make a Clyſter of the juyce of Lambs-tongue, Night-ſhade, or of Stancrop.</p>
               <p>Or, lay thereupon the pap of Barley-Meal, the rind of Pomgranats, with one of the three aforeſaid Juices.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="111" type="part">
               <head>111. <hi>Againſt the riſing of the Matrix.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Chafe the Legs downward, and tye them ſtiff: alſo bleed by Cupping-glaſſes upon the thigh: rub the belly downward, from the little hole of the Heart, unto the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel.</p>
               <p>Let the patient ſmell to ſuch things as ſtink; as burnt Partridge-feathers, ſhoo-ſoles: hold underneath her Gilliflowers, Marjoram, Amber-greaſe, Civet, or Wool-leaves, of the uppermoſt of the ſhoot.</p>
               <p>Alſo let her drink Wormwood-water, with Mithridate about the bigneſs of a bean.</p>
               <p>Or, fifteen red or black ſmall grains of Piony, bruiſed and put into White-wine: or, a leaf of great Burs laid under the hollow of the foot.</p>
               <p>Let the patient drink every night when ſhe goes to ſleep, three ſpoonfuls of white-Wine,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:59943:62"/> wherein an ounce of wild-Vine-root hath been ſoaked and boyled.</p>
               <p>If the woman be big with Child, let her lay cloſe with her Husband: he afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Remedies are dangerous for a woman with Child.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="112" type="part">
               <head>112. <hi>Againſt ſinking of the Matrix.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Let the patient vomit, rub her Arms, and tye them ſtiff, and ſet Cupping-glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes on the Breaſt, without pricking; let her ſmell to things well-ſcented: you may uſe below other ſtinking things; let her drink tart red-Wine, with powder of Harts-horn, or of dry Laurel-leaves.</p>
               <p>Or, make a Poultis of bruiſed Garlick mingled with water: or, of green bruiſed Nettles.</p>
               <p>This being put to the belly, will bring the Matrix to its place: or, take the leaves of Poppies boyled in Oyl and Quail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuet, and lay it to the belly as a Poultis: or, the aſhes of Egg-ſhells out of which Chickens have been hatched, mingled with pitch, and laid upon the belly: or, the leaf of great Burs laid under the hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of the foot, draws the Mother down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; but being laid to the Crown of the head, draws it upward.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="113" type="part">
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:59943:62"/>
               <head>113. <hi>For the white Flux.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Firſt, let the body be cleanſed, then drink the juyce of Lambs-tongue, or Purſlein-water, with Powder of Amber, Coral, Bolus Armenius, Terra-ſigillata, prepared Steel, Spunge burnt in a pot, and Sea-ſhells, firſt burnt, and then waſh'd in Wine and dryed.</p>
               <p>Concerning outward Remedies, make a Lye of the Aſhes of an Oak, Fig-tree-wood: or, of young Willow-trees, in which you ſhall boyl the rinds of Liver-wort or Crowfoot, <hi>(Heſtorta)</hi> Periwinckle, winter-Roſes, with a little vineger and ſalt; with this you ſhall make a Bath, and ſit therein to the middle of the body.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="114" type="part">
               <head>114. <hi>Againſt the Monthly Flux.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Let the patient drink the juyce of Lambs-tongue, with the powder of the dryed bones of Sheep: or, powder of St. James's ſhells, Coral, Harts-horn, burnt-Egg-ſhells: Powder of Fullers wool-cards, or Scales of Iron, firſt ſoaked in vineger, and made into powder.</p>
               <p>Concerning outward Remedies, lay on the Navel hedg-Snails well bruiſed: or,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:59943:63"/> the husks which lye between the ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels of the nuts, being burnt, bruiſed ſmall, and mingled with Wine: or, make a pap of Chimney-ſoot: or, take the black which is ſcraped from the bottom of a Kettle, mingled with the white of an Egg: or, the juyce of Dove-nettles, or of Wool-hearb; this you muſt lay upon the loyns, or the lower part of the Belly.</p>
               <p>Or, fill a great bag with bay-Salt, put it in freſh well-water, and lay it behind the hollow of the Loins.</p>
               <p>Or, the Gum of a black Cherry-tree, ſoaked in the juyce of Lambs-tongue, and put it into the Matrix by little ſpouts: or, lay upon the Breaſt the leaves of Salen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine.</p>
               <p>The greater part of the Remedies that are uſeful for this diſeaſe, are alſo good againſt the Bloody Flux; ſo alſo is the Dyet.</p>
               <p>The ſick perſon ſhould be in a place where the air is moderate, and abſtain from heat and cold; let her not work much, but ſleep long; let her rub her Arms and Shoulders, and bind her Arms hard from the ſhoulder to the elbow.</p>
               <p>Let her put Cupping-glaſſes under her Breaſts, on the back, and under the ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; let her avoid all perturbations of
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:59943:63"/> mind, as Anger, Sadneſs, Fear, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> let her eat a little and often; let her keep her belly looſe: Oppilation binds up the body, and cauſeth the preſſing down of the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dament, and motion of the blood.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="115" type="part">
               <head>115. <hi>To provoke the Monthly Flux in Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Give them to drink every morning two ounces of St. Johns Herb, or the Decocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Graſs, Nardus-ſeed, Cicers, the Roots of Ladies-mark, Radiſh, Cinna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Saffron, and Fullers-cards; to which you may add Myrrha, to the bigneſs of a bean.</p>
               <p>Or, the juyce of Eringo-Thiſtle, and of Fullers-Cards, mixed with white-wine.</p>
               <p>Outward Remedies may be theſe; make a Bath of River-water, wherein Mugwort, Mallow, Poppies, Camomile, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilots, and the like Herbs have been boiled. In this Bath rub the hips and the thighs downward, with a little bag full of St. Johns Herb, Chervil, Salendine, water-Parſley, Betony, Nardus-ſeed, and the like.</p>
               <p>Or, take a quarter of an ounce, or the eighth part of an ounce of Harts-marrow, wrap it in a fine linnen cloth, which muſt be put deep into the woman, after her
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:59943:64"/> body is prepared and purged.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="116" type="part">
               <head>116. <hi>Againſt Sterility or Barrenneſs.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Let the Barren Woman, (four days af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her Monthly Flux) drink the juyce of Sage, with a little Salt, continuing the ſame a long time.</p>
               <p>Or, take the Female of a Hart that is with young; kill her, and draw out her belly, the Fruit with its windings; take out the Fruit, and let the windings <hi>(Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundinae)</hi> be dried in an Oven, out of which Bread hath been newly drawn: then break into morſels that part of the wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings which was next to the Fruit, to a Powder.</p>
               <p>Give her this Powder to drink three mornings a little after midnight; with three or four ſpoonfuls of Wine; let her not riſe in four hours after ſhe hath taken this.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>This following Potion is of great virtue.</head>
                  <p>Take young ſprigs of wild Vine-leaves, of Agrimony, St. Johns Herb, Thouſand-leaves, Gamander, Goats-leaf, Harts-tongue, Pimpernel, field-Cypreſs, Violets green, of each an handful; one hundred
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:59943:64"/> Pepper-corns, Commin-ſeed half an ounce, A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gelica, fine Cinnamon, Galiga, Ginger, Cloves, Nutmegs, Spike, of each a quarter of an ounce: pound all theſe together, and let them ſoak two days in white-wine; boyl them to two third parts, then ſtrain the wine, and mingle therewith as much ſcum'd honey as is neceſſary: make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hereof a Syrup; let the Woman take of this in the morning and at night a ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, with Wine, or diſtilled water of the Herb Balm</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="117" type="part">
               <head>117. <hi>To prevent Miſcarrying.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Let her when ſhe is quick with Child, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ake of the Powder of Crimſon, or Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et-grain, and fine Frankinceſe, of each <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> like quantity, with the white of an Egg: or, the Powder of the Piſle of an Ox, (as is deſcribed in 66. for the Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſie.)</p>
               <p>Or, that ſhe always wear on her fingers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Diamond, which hath virtue to keep the Child in the Womb.</p>
               <p>Or, take a Snake, dry it; pounded and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pplied with crumb'd bread, 'tis very good to hinder Miſcarrying: but eſpecially the Eagle-ſtone being worn about the left ſhoulder, or hang'd on the ſame arm or
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:59943:65"/> ſide, keeps the Child in the Womb<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="118" type="part">
               <head>118. <hi>To quicken the pain of a Woman in Labour.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Tye within the thigh, near the Groin, an Eagle-ſtone: as ſoon as the Child is born, take the ſtone away, and give the Woman to drink, a Potion of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction of St. Johns-herb, Rhue, Depham, and Poppies: or, of the juyce of Parſley preſt out with vineger, or white-Wine, or Hypocras, wherein the Powder of the rinds of Caſſia, Cinnamon, Date-ſtones, and Roots, of Cypreſs, of red Eaſters flower-de-luce, and Camomile-flowers, or the juyce of Good Henry have been ſteep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; lay theſe with white-Wine, or the leaves of the ſame, upon, or round about the Matrix.</p>
               <p>If the Woman in Labour faint, give her Bread that hath been ſoaked in Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craſs, or a ſpoonful of Clarret-water, which is thus made.</p>
               <p>Take a pint of Brandy, grated Cinna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon about three ounces: having ſoaked three days, ſtrain it through a clean cloth, adding thereto one ounce of fine Sugar, Roſe-water ſix ounces, to a Claret-wine; let it ſtand in a well-ſtopped Glaſs for uſe.</p>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:59943:65"/>
               <p> This Water, or rather Wine, is not onely good againſt the Diſtempers of the Matrix, but againſt ſwouning, faintneſs, weakneſs of the ſtomach, and other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="119" type="part">
               <head>119. <hi>To cauſe the ſecond or after-Birth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>To cauſe it to come forth, the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid means are good; but you may take luke-warm the Powder of Beans, Saffron-flowers, or Marygolds, with white-Wine, or Hypocraſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="120" type="part">
               <head>120. <hi>Againſt following Pains.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Againſt after-following pains, drink a little ſpoonful of Claret-water, deſcribed before, Sect. 118. or, water of Peach-flowers: or, Powder of the Roots of Wall-wort, Peach-kernels, Nutmegs, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and Ambergreeſe, with white-Wine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Outward means, or a Pap to lay on the Belly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take hard boyled yolks of Eggs, and fry them with the Oyl of Nuts and Jeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min; add thereto Powder of Dill and Commin, or Flax-ſeed, Bean-meal, unſalted Butter, Oyl of Rhue, and Dill, with Powder of Camomile-leaves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="121" type="part">
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:59943:66"/>
               <head>121. <hi>For a diſturbed. Matrix.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Lay upon the Belly a Pap made of Cow-dung, Sheep or Goats-dung, with Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min, Aniſeed, Fenickle, and Parſley-ſeed, with a good quantity of Wine: or, in want of this Pap, you may cover the belly with a freſh-Net of Weather, Sheep, or Goat.</p>
               <p>Or, lay a diſh of Platanus-wood, or an earthen Cruiſe upon the Navel; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt anoint the corners of the Cruiſe with an head of Garlick.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="122" type="part">
               <head>122. <hi>Againſt Burſtenneſs, or a Rupture.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Lay upon the place a Pap of Bean-meal and Wine: or, a Pap of Wall-wort, Daſy, ſhip-pitch, and a little Maſtick, then lay thereupon a ſmall cloth, made wet in the juyce or moiſtneſs which floweth out of the little Fruits of the Elm-tree: or, make a Pap of that which remaineth in the Paper-mills after the Paper is made, and tye it thereupon.</p>
               <p>In the mean time drink for nine days together, a Potion prepared of the Roots of Solomons Seal and Sanickle.</p>
               <p>Or, put red-Snails in an earthen pot, dry
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:59943:66"/> them in an hot Oven, and make them into Powder; give this to Children for fifteen days together, or longer if neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty requireth, with Pap or Broth, if they ſuck; but if they be froward, then ſtill the Snails with hot water, and give it them fifteen days as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>Or, make a Powder of black-Bramble, and give them an eighth part of an ounce thereof in a morning for ſome days to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="123" type="part">
               <head>123. <hi>A Cure for the Gout.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take new wax and freſh Butter, of each two pounds, let it boil up together, then pour it thus hot into good Clarret-wine, as much as ſhall be neceſſary; when they are mixed together, take them out, and make them up in a Lump, of which you ſhall take ſome part, and lay it on the ill-affected part.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the leaves of Lyon-foot two hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls, Oyl of Linſeed eighteen ounces, white-Wine four pints and an half; boil it till it is half waſted; rub with this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction the painful place.</p>
                  <p>The ſame is performed with the Oyl of Spike, and juyce of white Poppies, of
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:59943:67"/> each a like quantity, with Oyl of Olives in which Frogs have been boiled till the fleſh goeth off from their bones.</p>
                  <p>Alſo Oyl of Cinnamon, Wax, and Salt, mix'd together, of each a like quantity. But againſt all ſorts of Gouts, 'tis good to lay upon the painful place a Poultis of red-Coleworts, with the juyce of wild-Elder, Bean-meal, Camomile-flowers, and Roſes groſly pounded: or, ſcraped Wall-wort, which is newly gathered, ſpread it upon a linnen cloth.</p>
                  <p>Or, take the Roots and Leaves of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, leaves of Scabioſa, Daiſy, and wild-Sage; boyl them in Wine together, ſtrain them, and add thereto Spike-oyl, Brandy, Ox-greaſe, of Cow-feet: or, take a gooſe pluck'd, and clean within; fill it with great Cheſnuts chop'd ſmall, and mingled with a little Salt; roaſt it, and keep the Cheſnuts for a chafing Salve.</p>
                  <p>Lay alſo on the pained place a little Doge, this will take away the pain.</p>
                  <p>But this is moſt excellent; make a plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Frogs, becauſe the chief Ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents are Frogs, <hi>(Emplaſtrum de Ranis)</hi> oyl of white flower-de-luce is very good, which operates better old than new.</p>
                  <p>That theſe Remedies may prove ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual, 'tis good to cleanſe exorbitant
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:59943:67"/> humours, that the Patient may be prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the application of neceſſary Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; therefore let him obſerve this dyet, let him drink but little wine, or rather not any.</p>
                  <p>Againſt the Gout in the hands and feet, uſe the decoction of St. Johns-herb in oyl of Olives, (as much as you ſhall judge ſufficient) boyl it two third parts, make it to an Oyntment or Chafing Salve, and anoint therewith the painful places; let the Patient drink the Decoction of wild-Cypreſs, with the eighth part of an ounce of Elder-berries.</p>
                  <p>Againſt the Gout of the Hip, lay on the painful place a pap made of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wheaten-loaf; that is, of the crums thereof, boyled in Cows or ſheeps-milk, adding thereto two yolks of Eggs, with a little Saffron; or make a Pap of the Roots and leaves of Mallowes, Roots of Marſh-Mallowes, or leaves of Violets, flowers of Camomile, and Melilots; boyl all together in water, or tripe-broth, and mix them or knead them together with the yolks of Eggs, Flax-ſeed, Meal, Hogs-ſuet, and oyl of Camomile.</p>
                  <p>Or, take Cow-dung, Bean-meal, whea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Rolls, and crum; knead them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with honey and vineger. If the
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:59943:68"/> painful place look whitiſh, and be much ſwelled, then add to the aforeſaid pap black pitch, with a little brimſtone; it is alſo good to preſs the juyce out of Ivy-leaves and Alder: then let it boyl with Oyl of Rhue, and Earth-worms, with a little wax, for an Oyntment or chafing Salve.</p>
                  <p>Or, a Poultis of Cow or Ox-dung, made warm in the aſhes, with Colewort or Vine-leaves; but if you will draw out the humour which lyeth in the joynts, then lay this Poultis thereon.</p>
                  <p>Take the dung of wild or tame Pigeons, oyl of old Tile, of each one ounce, Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den-creſs-ſeed, Muſtard-ſeed, of each a quarter of an ounce: mingle theſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="124" type="part">
               <head>124. <hi>A Cure for Red-ſwellings.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Make a Poultis of the leaves and flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Violets, leaves of Night-ſhade, flowers of Camomile, Hen-bane, and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilots boiled together in water-vineger.</p>
               <p>Strain it through a ſive, and lay it on the ſwelling: or, take the juyce of Stan-crop, a litte red-wine, and Barley-meal, make this into a pap; but in caſe there be an hardneſs by the ſwelling, then put
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:59943:68"/> hereupon Goats-dung, which will ſoften all hard-ſwellings, eſpecially the invete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate hardneſs of the knees; mingle it with Barley-meal, and water-vineger to a pap.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="125" type="part">
               <head>125. <hi>For Hard-ſwellings.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take Mallows, Poppies, Pellitory of the Wall, Wool-herb, Roots of Flower-de-luce, flowers of Camomile, and Mellilot, Poppies-ſeed and Flax-ſeed; boyl theſe together (of each a like quantity) in wine, water, and vineger: ſtrain them, then add thereto Meal of Beans and Barley, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Camomile and Roſes, Hens-greaſe, and freſh butter; make this to a Pap, and lay alſo upon the ſwelling an hot pap of the Lees of Bee-hives, mingled with white-wine, and fryed in a pan.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="126" type="part">
               <head>126. <hi>Againſt Windy-ſwellings.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take dried Salt, and put it between two ſmall cloaths upon the ſwelling: or, a Poul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis of the Lees of white-wine, wheaten-rolls, and Ox-dung newly made.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="127" type="part">
               <head>127. <hi>To ripen <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcerated Swellings.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Lay thereupon the dung of a Gooſe
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:59943:69"/> that hath faſted three days, after ſhe hath been fed with Eels newly killed; lay there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon long gnawed raw-wheat: or, a pap of the Roots and leaves of Mallow, white Poppies, Roots of flower-de-luce, and the Crums of a white-loaf: boyl theſe together, and ſtrain them: add hereunto the yolk of an Egg, and ſome Saffron. If it be a cold ſwelling, add to the decocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the pap, the Roots of wild-Alder, wild-vine, flowers of Camomile and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilots, Onion, with wheaten leaven.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="128" type="part">
               <head>128 <hi>Againſt Scratching, Scurvy, and other Itchings on the hands, or other parts of the body.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take luke-warm Smiths-water, put therein an handful of Salt, and rub the hands or other parts therewith; and when the Scabs are dry, anoint it with the Cream of Cows-milk.</p>
               <p>Or, take two parts of Venetian Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine, waſhed five or ſix times in Roſe-water, or other cold water: add hereunto a good quantity of Butter newly ſalted, the yolk of an Egg, and the juyce of a ſowre Orange, make this into a Salve; chafe herewith the Itchy place before the fire.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:59943:69"/>
                  <head>For young Children.</head>
                  <p>Take the juyce of Nettles, and Pop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar-ſalve, mingled together: or, ſoot of the Chimney, with ſtrong vineger; rub the itching place red, and then anoint it therewith.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="129" type="part">
               <head>129. <hi>To bring an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcer to Diſtillation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take raw wheat long eares, or Wheat-meal, the yolk of an Egg, Honey, and Hogs-greaſe; make thereof a plaiſter, and lay it to the Boil.</p>
               <p>Or, lay thereupon ſheeps-dung ſoaked in wine-vineger, if you will ſuppurate the Ulcers and make them ſoft: or, make a pap of Bean-meal, of Womans-milk, leaven, and large figs, and apply it to the Ulcers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="130" type="part">
               <head>130. <hi>Againſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers and Swellings about the Nails.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Lay upon it a little Worm which is is found in the midſt of Fuller-Cards when they are dry.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="131" type="part">
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:59943:70"/>
               <head>131. <hi>Againſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>leers that are hard to be Cured.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Gather May-dew before Sun-riſing, wring your ſheets in which you gather the dew; boyl, and ſcum it: while it boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, put into it Lint of fine-linnen, and lay them upon the Ulcers: when you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to ſee freſh or clean fleſh, then boyl in the dew a little Alum, and white-Frankincenſe, by this means you ſhall cure it.</p>
               <p>Or, take Powder of Oyſter-ſhells, raw or burnt: or, the dung of a Dog, who hath eaten for three days together nothing but bones: or, make a powder of rotten-Wood.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="132" type="part">
               <head>132. <hi>Againſt a Canker.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take honey of Roſes, Maſe, Alum, Salt, and white-Wine; boyl theſe together to the half; ſtrain this water through a cloth, and keep it to waſh the Canker: or, the diſtilled Water of Cow-dung.</p>
               <p>Againſt the Canker called <hi>Noli me ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere,</hi> which is the worſt of Cankers, lay Tobacco upon it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="133" type="part">
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:59943:70"/>
               <head>133. <hi>To take away Knobs.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take old and rotten Cheeſe, bruiſe it with Water where Bacon hath been boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; make it into a Plaiſter, and lay it upon the knobs.</p>
               <p>Or, bruiſe Corulus Indi, (which cometh out of the <hi>Levant)</hi> with Mirtle<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and wine-vineger, and lay it upon the knobs.</p>
               <p>Or, take nine pints of the Urin of a man, Balm, Canker-flowers, of each two handfuls; let them boil ſlowly in a new well-ſtopped earthen pot, to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of the half; then preſs out the herbs, and put thereto Brandy that is ſtrained through, four ounces; boil theſe together half an hour, and add thereto Oyl of Roſemary, and of Spike, of each one ounce, Quick-ſilver a quarter of an ounce; mingle theſe together with a flat-ſpoon to a Salve, with which you muſt chafe the knobs before the fire.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="134" type="part">
               <head>134. <hi>Againſt an hurt by a fall.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Let them drink white-Wine, with the 16th part of an ounce of Powder, made of Mummy, Tormentil, Raponticum, and Parmacety: or, Garden-Creſſes, prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:59943:71"/> ſeed of Houſleek, and Sugar-candy; of each an equal part.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="135" type="part">
               <head>135. <hi>Againſt blew ſpots.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Soak a little bag full of Salt in boyling-water, and bath the ſpots therewith.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="136" type="part">
               <head>136. <hi>A Cure for freſh Wounds.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take Garden-balſome, Wall-wort, Dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, and a little Salt; pound theſe together, and lay them on the Wound.</p>
               <p>Or, drop into it the juyce of Tobacco: or, lay on the juyce with its Herb, (which is beſt) this will heal it in three days: or, take Elm-Apples, flowers of St. Johns-Herb, Roſemary, and knobs of Roſes; put theſe together in a glaſs, with Oyl of Olives; ſtop it cloſe, and put it in the Sun, until by conſuming it ſeemeth to be rotten; ſtrain it ſeveral times through a linnen-cloth, keep it in a glaſs, and when you ſee occaſion, drop ſome of it into the Wound.</p>
               <p>Or, make a Salve of the juyce and leaves of Tobacco: or, take green Agri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, Betony, Pimpernel, of each one handful; pound them together in a Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and put them into a glazed pot,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:59943:71"/> with four pints and an half of white-Wine: cover them well, and boyl them upon a gentle and clear fire, to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of the half; cool it by little and little, the next day make it a little warm, and ſtrain it through a ſive as much as you can, adding thereto white-pitch, (melted apart) one pound, wax half a pound, Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine and Maſtick, of each one ounce; mingle theſe to a Salve.</p>
               <p>Beſides, make a Plaiſter of black Roſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitch, Brimſtone, and white Frankin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, of each a like quantity; bruiſe theſe, and mix them with the white of an Egg: lay it upon the wound after the blood is ſtanched, waſhed off, and the wound cloſe up; bind up the Wound with Cobwebs, and Rowlers; let them lye for ſeveral days on it.</p>
               <p>Or, boyl the leaves of Carduus Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictus in Wine, with Wheaten-meal, till it be as thick as a Salve; then waſh the Wound with Wine twice a day, and dreſs it with this Salve.</p>
               <p>Or, waſh the Wound with a decoction of Canker-flowers: or, (which is more expedient) take dirt from under the pails, and lay it to the Wounds, which will heal it preſently.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="137" type="part">
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:59943:72"/>
               <head>137. <hi>Againſt old and new Wounds.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take the leaves of Lambs-tongue, Dogs-rib, Mallows, good-Henry, noble-Sage, of each a handful. Theſe Herbs being well waſhed and diſtilled, muſt be pounded; then take of Hogs-greaſe the fourth part of an ounce melt it in a pan, and boyl it with the aforeſaid Herbs, till the juyce of the Herbs is conſumed.</p>
               <p>Add thereto Virgins-wax, Roſyn, Pitch, of each about the bigneſs of two Nuts, Frankincenſe half as much: melt them again, and make them into a Salve, this is good for all ſorts of Wounds.</p>
               <p>Or, take pounded and fifted Brimſtone, put it into a glaſs with Oyl of Olives, till it ſtand four or five fingers thick above it; then let the glaſs ſtand ten days in the Sun, ſtirring it often with a wooden-ſtick, keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the glaſs well-covered, that no duſt fall into it: after ten days pour the clear O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, (which by that time will draw the virtue of the Brimſtone to it) into another glaſs without ſpilling any of the brimſtone<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then ſtop it faſt; and when you uſe it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> dip therein lint of a clean cloth, or cotton<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or black-wooll, and lay it on the Wound<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Boyl, or ſwelling, every day till it be hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led:
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:59943:72"/> you may put Oyl upon the ſame Brimſtone, out of which Oyl hath been once poured.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="138" type="part">
               <head>138. <hi>Of Wounds by a Bullet.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>If the Bullet ſticks in the Wound, and you would get it out, make a tent of a Quince-Apple, or of Marmalade, anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Oyl and Eggs, and put it into the Wound.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="139" type="part">
               <head>139. <hi>Againſt ſtrained Sinews.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take ripe berries of Elder fill there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with a round flask half full with the oyl of Olives; ſtop the Glaſs well, and let it ſtand twenty four hours in a skillet of boyling-water, then put it ten days in a dunghil.</p>
               <p>Or, oyl of Elder, thus: fill a glaſed pot half full with the juyce of Elder-leaves, and fill it with the oyl of Olives; ſtop it cloſe with dough, put it into an Oven after the bread is drawn, and let it ſtand there untill the juyce be wholly conſumed.</p>
               <p>But this is more expedient; lay upon the Sinew the dung of an Ox or Cow, fryed in a pan with ſtrong vineger, or oyl of Acorns, or Gum of a wild Pear-tree,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:59943:73"/> mingled with Capons-greaſe, or oyl of Siccamore-Tree, or Jaſmin.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="140" type="part">
               <head>140. <hi>Againſt ſtung Sinews.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take Snails with the ſhells, pound them ſmall, and put thereto duſt-meal, which is on the walls of Mills; put this upon the Sinews: or, anoint them with the oyl of Earth-worms.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="141" type="part">
               <head>141. <hi>For Sinews that are cut through.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take unwaſhed Earth-worms, pound them ſmall, and lay them on the woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Sinews: or, lay Alder-flowers to ſoak or ſteep in the Sun, in oyl of Nuts, or in Balſom, or oyl, and dreſs the Sinew with it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="142" type="part">
               <head>142. <hi>For inward Wounds.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>If they may not be tented, drink the decoction of Eringo-Thiſtle, and waſh the outward Wound therewith.</p>
               <p>Alſo, take of Bramble-berries, ſtinging-Nettles, Marygoulds, Sanickle, Mouſe-ear, Pimpernel, green-Sene, Canker-flowers, Lambs-tongue, little tops of Hemp, Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male-Ferne, Ox-tongue, Gentiana, Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:59943:73"/> Aſh-keys, Pennyroyal, Scordium, Nip, Ruperts-herb, five-finger-herb, Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus-hair of all kinds, Roots of Madder, Sage, the whole Wallwort, St. Johns-herb, Daiſies, Betony, Agrimony, Brunella, of each an handful, flowers that ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the heart, four ounces of St. Johns-herb, Carduus Benedictus ſeed, long Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſtoned, Liquoris, of each an ounce; all theſe being well waſhed, muſt be very well pounded and ſtrained, with one pint of white-wine, to a Potion.</p>
               <p>Let the wounded perſon drink hereof before dinner and ſupper: if this drink be unpleaſant to him, then inſtead of pounding, boyl the above-mentioned In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients in common-water, and add there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to white-Wine, honey of Roſes, Syrrup of dry-Roſes, as much as ſhall be neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
               <p>Cleanſe the Wound with luke-warm white-Wine, and lay thereupon freſh, red, and warm'd leaves of Coleworts; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear ſalt-meats, Spices, ſtrong-Wine, great labour, and women.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="143" type="part">
               <head>143. <hi>Againſt the biting of a Mad-Dog.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Eat ſweet brier-wort, and waſh the hurt with a young Childs Piſs, or with a
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:59943:74"/> decoction of Rhue, Figs, red-Coleworts, and Salt mingled with honey and butter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="144" type="part">
               <head>144. <hi>To Cure the Biting of a Serpent.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take immediately a draught of the juyce of an Aſh-tree, with white-Wine, and lay upon the bed (of the party bitten) the leaves out of which the juyce was preſſed: or, the milky juyce of the Fig-tree, or juyce of Figs: or, Muſtard-ſeed bruiſed with vineger.</p>
               <p>Or, take the leaves of Wool-herb, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryophilate, red-Currans, of each an hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; boil them in vineger and Mares-piſs, of each a like quantity, until the half be conſumed to a Potion.</p>
               <p>Drink of this at once a ſmall drinking-glaſs; bath the Wound with the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the pecoction.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="145" type="part">
               <head>145. <hi>A Cure for Kibe-heels.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take the burnt-aſhes of old ſhoo-ſoles, mingle them with oyl of Roſes, and anoint therewith the Kibes,: or, lay thereupon Granate-ſhells boyled in Wine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="146" type="part">
               <head>146. <hi>A Cure for ſtinking Feet.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Put in your ſhooes the ſcales of Iron; if you will preſerve your health, keep your body clean, and purge out (ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly)
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:59943:74"/> ſuperfluous humours, therefore uſe gentle Purges, <hi>viz.</hi> Clyſters, Pills, or ſmall Potions, to prevent thereby great ſickneſſes.</p>
               <p>As, take a Clyſter every Month, to keep the body in good order, take purging Pills by the Advice of your Phyſician: Pills of Aloe, Myrrha wet with Wine, or the Syrrup of Venus-hair, which is good againſt fleam, and being taken once a week, 'tis good for the ſtomach, ſight, and hearing.</p>
               <p>When your ſtomach is ſtopped, you may looſen it, by taking the eighth part of an ounce of the Powder of the leaves of Damask-Roſes, with broth made of fleſh, a little before dinner, or with Caſſia alone.</p>
               <p>In the Spring you may cleanſe and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urge humours, with the decoction of pale-Roſes: drink eight or nine mornings together, one ſpoonful in a morning; or without reſpect to the ſeaſon of the year, you may purge with theſe Fleſh-broths.</p>
               <p>Take a young Hen, or a quarter thereof: or, boyl Weather-Mutton that is not very fat; add thereto good Herbs, as Berna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, Sorrel, Lettice, tame and wild; Cicory, of each a little quantity, <hi>viz.</hi> an hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; when it is boyled, ſtrain it through a cloth into a well-glazed-pot, and adde
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:59943:75" rendition="simple:additions"/> thereto Sena-leaves, Cinnamon, and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſeed, of each a little; then ſtop the pot very cloſe, that the vapours may not fly out: put it on a fire, and let it boyl up one boyling onely; then take it from the fire, and let it ſtand a whole night upon hot aſhes; the next morning ſtrain it through a clean cloth, and add to it Syrrup of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, one ounce and an half; boyl it to a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: take a little of this (made warm) about five hours before dinner, in Spring and Harveſt; they are the beſt times, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe then Herbs are beſt in their ſeaſon, but better in the Spring than in the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt. The Apozemata or herb-Potions, purge fundamentally, yet gently, becauſe of the divers vertue of Herbs of which they are made. Add to this Potion Rhabar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar, leaves of Sene, Agarins; alſo little Cakes of Cinnamon, Sugar, and other things, according to the condition and complexion of the Patients body.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Another Purging Remedy.</head>
                  <p>Take Virgin-honey one pound, Powder of Agarius, of Folia-Sene, of one of three, or of all three four ounces; mingle this Powder with honey, let it ſtand ſixty days in a cool-place, in a pot well covered, ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it every day, and take off the Scum.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:59943:75"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
